本字幕由  独立字幕组  原创译制
更多字幕请访问 idpsub.webflow.io
翻译：瓶子  Mao   SeanZhang
时间轴&校对：SeanZhang  瓶子
特效&总监：SeanZhang
独立字幕组
IDPSUB
-=本字幕由 第三楼字幕网 独家首发=-
电影字幕下载 请访问http://www.disanlou.org
时间轴/后期：包大人
人
火
星
攵
救
扌
援
阿
西
达
利
亚
平
原
_
好了, 全队保持在视线内
Alright team, stay in sight of each other.
美
国
航
天
局
-
阿
瑞
今天要让美航局自豪
Let's make NASA proud today.
斯
着
陆
点
_
任
务
天
数
：
第
太
阳
日
那儿什么样, 沃特尼?
How's it looking over there, Watney?
嗯, 你肯定乐意听到
Well, you'll be happy to hear that in
区块14到28里的颗粒都特别粗糙
grid section 14 to 28, the particles were phenomenally coarse,
到了29, 这儿的......这儿的颗粒好一些
and on 29, they're.... they're much finer,
应该是理想的化学分析样本
which should be ideal for chemical analysis.
哦, 哇, 大伙儿听到没有?
Oh, wow. Did everybody hear that?
马克刚发现了灰尘, 我们是不是要通知媒体了?
Mark just discovered dirt. Should we alert the media?
好了, 你今天做什么了, 马丁内斯?
It's alright. What're you doing today, Martinez?
一直在确保飞行器立着?
Making sure that the MAV is still upright?
呃, 我想你知道目视检查仪器
Well, I like you know that visual inspection of the equipment
对于任务成功可是至关重要
is imperative to mission success.
我也要报告飞行器还立着
I also like to report that the MAV is still upright.
沃特尼, 你的频道一直开着
Watney, you're keep leaving your channel open,
导致马丁内斯回应
which leads to Martinez responding,
导致我们都听见了, 导致本小姐很烦
which leads to all our listening, which leads to me being annoyed.
收到马丁内斯, 队长想请你
Roger that.   Martinez, the captain would like you to please...
关上你的伶牙俐齿
shut your smart mouth.
我们喜欢用不一样的词来形容马丁内斯的嘴
We prefer to use a different adjective to describe Martinez's mouth.
- 哟, 刚才贝克是骂了我嘛? - 叫贝克博士, 是的
- Oh, did Beck just insult me? - Dr. Beck, and, yes.
只要你一声令下, 指挥官
I'll be happy to turn the radios off from here, commander.
我很乐意把它关了
Just say the word.
嘿, 约翰森保持通话是整个......
Hey, Johanssen. Constant communication is the whole...
让他闭嘴
Shut him off.
替我的老乡抱歉了, 沃格尔
Apologise for my countrymen, Vogel.
接受道歉我们需要多少样本, 指挥官?
Accepted. How many samples do we need, commander?
7组, 每组一百克
7, a hundred grams each.
我们有个任务更新, 风暴预警
We have a mission update. Storm warning.
指挥官, 你得进来, 你肯定想看看这个
Commander, you should come inside. You're going to want to see this.
- 什么东西? - 风暴预警
- What is it? - Storm warning.
我在早上的简报里看到了, 我们会赶在风暴之前回舱
I saw that in this morning's briefing. We'll be inside before it hits.
没错, 他... 他们更新了估算
Yeah. They- They upgraded their estimate.
风暴要严重得多
The storm is going to be a lot worse.
马丁内斯, 风暴看起来怎么样?
Martinez, how's it look?
不妙
Not good.
直径1200千米, 偏角24.41度
1200 km in diameter bearing 24.41 degrees
这是直奔着我们来啊
That's trekking right towards us.
根据现在的估算, 估计力度为8600牛
Base on current estimation, estimated force of 8600 Newtons.
- 终止力度呢? - 7500牛
- What's the abort force. - 7500.
只要超过, 飞行器就会翻
Anything more than that and the MAV will tip.
- 我们撤吗? - 启动终止程序
- Do we scrub? - Begin abort procedure.
我们还在估算临界误差是多少......我们能不能等等结果?
We are estimating where the marginal error would be... could we wait it out?
等等结果吧
Let's wait it out.
指挥官
Commander.
准备紧急脱离
Prep emergency departure.
- 指挥官 - 我们撤, 这是命令
- Commander. - We're scrubbed, that's an order.
马丁内斯, 起飞还需要多长时间?
Martinez, how long before take off?
10分钟
10 minutes.
能见度几乎为零
Visibility is almost zero.
谁走散了, 就追踪我宇航服的信号
Anyone gets lost, home in on my suit's telemetry.
- 你准备好了? - 好了!
- You ready? - Ready!
- 指挥官, 你还好吗? - 我很好
- Commander, are you okay? - I'm okay.
指挥官, 现在10度了, 飞行器正在向12.3度倾斜
Commander, we're at 10 degrees, and the MAV's going to tip at 12.3
嘿!我们也许能让飞行器立住
Hey! We might be able to keep the MAV from tipping.
我们怎么做?
How?
用太阳能电站的电缆作牵引绳!
Use the cables from the solar farm as guylines!
用火星车当锚!
Anchor it with a Rover!
小心!
Watch out!
啊啊啊啊!
Aahhhhh!
沃特尼!
Watney!
警告：检测到宇航服破损
WARNING SUIT BREACH DETECTED.
- 怎么了? - 他被击中了
- What happened? - He was hit.
沃特尼, 回话
Watney, report.
失去信号之前, 他的失压警报响了
Before we lose telemetry, his decompression alarm went off.
- 约翰森, 你上次看见他是在哪儿? - 他离线了
- Johanssen, where did you last see him? - He's offline.
- 我不... 我不知道他在哪儿 - 他宇航服上的生理指标怎么样?
- I can't, I don't know where he is. - What are the vitals on his suit?
- 他不在线, 他不在线 - 没用, 我们完全失去了沃特尼的信号
- He's offline. He's offline. - Negative. Complete lost of signal on Watney.
- 米契? - 在
- Mitch? - Yeah.
他能在失压下挺多久?
How long can he survive decompression?
不到一分钟
Less than a minute.
一列纵队, 向西前进
Line up. Walk west.
他可能倒下了, 我们别踩到他
He maybe prone, we don't want to step over him.
指挥官, 现在10.5度了, 向11度倾斜
Commander, we're at 10.5 degrees, tilting to 11.
有一阵强风
We got a gust of wind.
收到
Copy that.
全体都有, 追踪马丁内斯的宇航服
Everyone, home in on Martinez's suit.
你们会回到气密舱, 进去, 准备发射
It'll get you to the airlock. Get in, prep for launch.
那你怎么办, 指挥官?
What about you, commander?
我要再找一会儿
I'm going to search a little longer.
别呆着了, 走!
Keep moving. Go!
沃特尼, 沃特尼, 回话
Watney. Watney, report.
飞行器11.6度了, 来一阵小阴风我们就翻了
The MAV is at 11.6 degrees. Once good gust and we're tipping.
如果要翻, 你就发射
If it tips, you launch.
你真以为我会抛下你?
You really think I'm going to leave you behind?
这是命令, 马丁内斯
That's an order, Martinez.
马克!
Mark!
马克, 能听到吗?
Mark. Can you hear me?
马丁内斯, 防撞雷达行吗?
Martinez, what about the proximity radar?
它能不能检测到, 沃特尼的宇航服
Could that detect, Watney's suit.
呃, 它是用来检测轨道里的赫尔墨斯号的
Uh. It's made to see the Hermes in orbit,
而不是一件衣服里的一小片铁
not a little piece of metal put in a single suit.
- 试试吧 - 收到
- Give it a try. - Roger.
她在想什么?她明知道红外线不能穿过沙暴
What is she thinking? She knows the infrared can't get through a sand storm.
她不肯放弃一线希望
She is grasping for anything.
防撞雷达无联络
We got negative contact on the proximity radar.
- 没有? - 嗯
- Nothing? - Nah.
我几乎看不见居住舱了
I can barely see the Hab.
指挥官, 我知道你不想听, 不过......
Commander, I know you don't want to hear this but...
马克死了
Mark is dead.
指挥官
Commander.
嘿, 你发什么神经, 大哥?
Hey. What the hell is wrong with you, man?
我的朋友刚刚死了, 我不想让我的指挥官陪葬
My friend just died, I don't want my commander to die too.
失衡警告
STABILITY WARNING
我们会回来的!
WE'LL COME BACK !
指挥官, 你得回飞船了, 马上!
Commander, you need to get back to the ship, now.
13度
13 degrees.
如果我们失衡了, 就再也正不过来了
If we past balance, we'll never rock back.
我还有一招没用, 然后我再听从指令, 指挥官
I got one more trick left, and then I'm following orders, commander.
你在用轨道机动系统?
You're firing the OMS?
是的
That's right.
指挥官!
Commander!
我在路上
On my way.
约翰森, 咱们走吧
Johanssen, let's go.
马克
Mark.
稳定在11.5度
We're 11.5 and holding.
准备就绪, 随时待命
Ready to go on your command.
发射就绪
Ready to launch.
指挥官
Commander.
我需要你的口令, 做还是不做
I need you to verbally tell me whether or not to.
发射
Launch.
中部标准时间, 上午4:30许
At around 4:30 AM, central standard time,
我们的卫星检测到有风暴
our satellites detected a storm
逼近火星阿瑞斯3号任务点
approaching the Ares 3 mission site on Mars.
6:45, 风暴进一步恶劣
At 6:45, the storm has escalated to severe
我们别无他法, 只好中止任务
and we have no choice but to abort the mission.
归功于路易斯队长的随机应变
Thanks to the quick action of Captain Lewis,
宇航员贝克、约翰森、马丁内斯和沃格尔
astronaut Beck, Johanssen, Martinez and Vogel
都得以登上火星爬升装置
were all able to reach the Mars ascend vehicle.
并于中央时7:28执行了紧急发射
And performed an emergency launch at 7:28 central time.
不幸的是, 在撤离过程中
Unfortunately during the evacuation,
宇航员马克·沃特尼被碎片击中罹难
astronaut Mark Watney was struck by debris and killed.
路易斯指挥官及其小队其余成员死里逃生
Commander Lewis and the rest of her team were able to intercept safety
回到赫尔墨斯号, 现在正在返航
with the Hermes and now are heading home.
马克·沃特尼, 遇难
But Mark Watney, is dead.
- 桑德斯先生 - 桑德斯先生
- Mr. Sanders. - Mr. Sanders.
- 桑德斯先生 - 桑德斯先生!
- Mr. Sanders. - Mr. Sanders!
氧气浓度：极低
OXYGEN LEVEL : CRITICAL
氧气浓度：极......
OXYGEN LEVEL : CRITI...
压力：稳定
PRESSURE : STABLE
哇啊啊啊啊!
AWWWW!
好吧
Okay.
居住舱
>
睡舱
第19太阳日
压力
温度
氧气
好吧
Okay.
你好, 我是马克·沃特尼, 宇航员
Hello, this is Mark Watney, astronaut.
我记录这个日志并保存
I'm entering this log for the record,
是为了, 万一我没能挺住
because, in case I don't make it.
现在是6:53
It is 06:53
第19太阳日, 而且
on Sol 19, and
我还活着
I'm alive.
废话, 不过
Obviously. But...
我猜对于我的队友以及美航局来说, 这可是个惊喜
I'm guessing that's going to come as a surprise to my crew mates and to NASA.
也是全世界的惊喜, 真的, 所以
And to the entire world, really. So...
惊喜
Surprise.
我没死在第18太阳日, 也算是最好的结果了
I did not die on Sol 18 and best I can figure.
这一段主通讯天线断掉了
This length of our primary communication antenna broke off
击穿了我的生理监测器
and threw it through my bio- monitor.
也给我开了个口子
and ripped a hole in me as well.
不过天线和血液也确实
But the antenna and the blood really
成功堵住了我宇航服的裂口, 让我活了下来
managed to seal the breach in my suit which kept me alive,
但尽管如此, 队员们一定以为我死了
even though the crew must have thought I was dead.
我没办法联系美航局
I have no way to contact NASA.
而且即使可以, 也要
And even if I could, it's going to be...
等4年才能有载人任务来救我
4 years until a manned mission can reach me.
而且我在的居住舱设计上能维持31天
And I'm in a Hab designed to last 31 days.
如果充氧器损坏, 我就会窒息
If the oxygenator breaks, I'm going to suffocate.
如果再生水装置损坏, 我就会渴死
If the water reclaimer breaks, I'll die of thirst.
如果居住舱破损, 我就会像是......被挤爆
If the Hab breaches, I'm just kind of... implode.
如果好运的话这些都没发生
And if by some miracle none of that happens,
最终我将会耗尽食物
eventually I'm going to run out of food.
所以
So.
是啊
Yeah.
我不要在这里狗带
I'm not going to die here.
第21太阳日
SOL 21
32.
33.
34.
35、36份酸甜鸡
35, 36. Sweet & Sour chicken.
好吧, 咱们来算个数
Alright. Let's do the math.
我们在这儿的服务设施只用来维持
Our service mission here was suppose to last
31太阳日, 为了打出富余, 他们放了68天的食物
for 31 Sols. For redundancy they sent 68 Sols worth of food,
是给6个人吃的
that's for 6 people.
所以只有我的话, 可以坚持300太阳日
So for just me, that's going to last 300 Sols.
我觉得节约一下可以撑到400太阳日, 所以
Which I figure I could stretch to 400 if I ration. So...
我得想个法子, 在这儿把
I got to figure out a way, to grow
3年的口粮种出来
3 years worth of food here.
种在一个寸草不生的星球
On a planet where nothing grows.
幸运的是
Luckily.
我是个植物学家
I'm a botanist.
而火星, 将会畏惧
And Mars, will come to fear
我大植物学的力量
my botany powers.
有机垃圾
ORGANIC WASTE
生物危害 人类排泄物
BIOHAZARD HUMAN - WASTE
男 沃特尼
M. WATNEY
压力：稳定
PRESSURE : STABLE
缝合钉出来了
Staple came out.
操你妈, 火星
Fuck you, Mars.
约翰森, 天哪
Johanssen, Jesus.
问题是水
The problem is water.
我弄了126平米的土
I have created 126 square meters of soil.
每立方米土需要48升水
And every cubic meter of soil requires 48 liters of water
才能种植
to be farm with.
所以, 我得造出来更多水才行
So, I'm got to make a lot more water.
好在我知道方法
Good thing is that I know the recipe.
采集氢气, 加入氧气, 然后烧之
You take hydrogen, you add oxygen,you burn them.
现在, 我飞行器里有好几百升没用过的肼
Now, I have hundreds of liters of unused hydrazine at the MDV.
我将肼用铱催化
I run the hydrazine around an iridium catalyst
它会分解为氮气和氢气
It will separate into N2 and H2.
而我只要把氢气集中在一小块然后点燃
And if I just direct the hydrogen into a small area and burn it,
简直就是重塑了人类历史
likely remake history of humanity.
点氢气从来不会有什么坏处
Nothing bad has ever happened from lighting hydrogen on fire.
美航局讨厌火
NASA hates fire
因为总的来说, 在太空, 火是人类杀手
because of the whole, fire makes everybody die in space thing.
所以, 他们送来这儿的所有东西都是阻燃的
So, everything they sent us up here with is flame retardant, with...
显然不包括
the notable exception of...
马丁内斯的个人物品
Martinez's personal items.
对不起, 马丁内斯, 如果你不想让我翻你的东西
I'm sorry, Martinez, if you didn't want me to go through your stuff,
你就不应把我丢在这颗荒星上等死
you shouldn't left me for dead on a desolate planet.
话说, 我估计你也不会在意
By the way, I'm figuring you're going to be fine with this,
考虑到我现在的状况
given my present situation.
靠你了
Counting on you.
那么, 是的, 我炸到自己了
So, yeah. I blew myself up.
我猜最可能是
Best guess.
我忘了
I forgot to...
考虑额外的氧气
account for the excess oxygen that...
供我呼吸, 之前在计算的时候
I've been exhaling when I did my calculations,
因为我蠢
because I'm stupid.
是啊, 只要我的耳朵停止耳鸣
Yeah, I'm going to get back to work here,
我还要回来接着做
just as soon as my ear stop ringing.
有趣的附注：其实喷气推进实验室就是这么建立的
Interesting side note, this is actually how the jet propulsion lab was founded
加州理工的5个人, 试着做
5 guys at Caltec, trying to make
火箭燃料, 几乎烧掉了自己的宿舍
rocket fuel and they nearly burned down their dorm.
学校没有开除他们, 而是把他们赶到附近的农场里
And rather than expel them, banished them to a nearby farm
让他们继续研究
tell them to keep working.
于是我们就有了太空计划
And then we have a space program.
成了
Okay.
嘿, 你好
Hey, there.
上帝垂青美国, 让马克参与我们的太空计划
The nation was blessed, to have Mark serving in our space program.
在沉痛悼念他的同时
While his lost will be deeply felt,
美航局的诸位都将坚持不懈
the men and women of NASA will soldier forth,
全力以赴, 做好自己的职责
onward and upward, in the mission of their agency.
泰
迪
·
桑
德
斯
美
航
局
以继承马克遗志
By doing so they honor the legacy Mark's leaving behind.
长
确保他的牺牲没有白费
To ensure his sacrifice will not be in vain.
约
翰
逊
航
天
中
心
休
斯
顿
,
德
州
我觉得你的演讲很不错, 就是顺带一说
I thought you gave a lovely speech, by the way.
﹣我需要你批准调用卫星 - 想都别想
- I need you to authorize my satellite time. - It's not going to happen.
我们被资助了5次阿瑞斯任务
We're funded for 5 ARES missions.
我认为我能让议会批准第6个
I think I can get congress to authorize a 6th.
听着, 阿瑞斯3号才18个太阳日就撤了
Look, ARES 3 evac'd after 18 Sols.
那儿, 那儿还搁着一半任务的物资呢
There's- There's half a mission worth of supplies up there.
我只要付出普通任务的一小部分代价就可以卖掉它
I can sell it at a fraction of the cost of a normal mission.
我只要知道, 我们的财产还剩下多少
And all I have to know is, what's left of our assets.
你不是唯一一个需要调用卫星的人
You're not the only one who needs satellite time.
我们阿瑞斯4号的供应任务马上就要开始
We got the ARES 4 supply missions coming up.
我们应该多关注斯基阿帕雷利陨石坑
We should be focusing on the Schiaparelli crater.
好吧, 我们有12颗卫星在上面飞, 肯定能富余出来几小时的
Okay, we got 12 satellites up there, surely we can spare a few hours.
不是调用卫星的问题, 文斯
It's not about satellite time, Vince.
我们是公有领域组织
We're a public domain organization.
- 我们在这件事上要透明 - 好吧
- We need to be transparent on this. - Okay.
我们把卫星瞄向居住舱那一霎
The second we point the satellites to the Hab,
我就已经把马克·沃特尼尸体的照片播放给全世界了
I broadcast pictures of Mark Watney's dead body to the world.
你在担心公关问题?
You're afraid of a PR problem?
我当然担心公关问题, 还提什么任务?
Of course I'm afraid of a PR problem. Another mission?
议会连一个曲别针都不会给我们报销
Congress won't reimburse us for a paper clip
只要我们把死掉的宇航员挂在华盛顿邮报的首页上
if I put a dead astronaut out on the front page of the Washington Post.
他也不能不翼而飞啊, 泰迪我是说, 他不会......
He's not going anywhere, Teddy. I mean, he's not...
他不会降解掉的
he's not going to decompose.
知道吧, 他会永远在那儿
You know, he's going to be up there forever.
气象学家估计他会被沙子覆盖
Meteorology estimates that he'll be covered in sand
在正常的天气活动下只需要一年
from normal weather activity within a year.
我们不能等上一年, 我们有活儿要干
We can't wait a year, we got work to do.
阿瑞斯5号都不会在5年内发射, 我们时间充裕
ARES 5 won't even launch for 5 years, we've plenty of time.
好吧
Okay.
好吧, 考虑一下
Okay, consider this.
现在
Right now,
全世界站在我们这边
the world is on our side.
对沃特尼家人的同情
Sympathy for the Watney family.
阿瑞斯6号可以让他落叶归根
ARES 6 can bring his body home
现在, 我们不说这就是任务的目的
Now. We don't say that's the purpose of the mission,
不过要明确这是任务的一部分
but we make it clear that would be a part of it.
如果我们这样描述
If we frame it that way.
议会会给予更多支持, 但等上一年可就不会了
More support from congress, but not if we wait a year.
我们等上一年, 就没人鸟你了
We wait a year nobody gives a shit.
任
务
控
制
中
心
美
航
局
约
翰
逊
航
天
中
心
休
斯
顿
,
德
州
明
迪
·
帕
克
卫
星
通
讯
美
航
局
发件人：文森特·卡普尔
收到信息
文森特·卡普尔
Vincent Kapoor.
嗨，明迪
检查一下这个坐标：
纬度：46°  42' 0"
经度：22°  0'  0"
（46.7º，-22º）
文森特
--
阿西达里亚平原
ACIDALIA PLANITIA
啥?
What?
你好, 保卫处
Hi, security.
我是卫星通信的明迪·帕克
This is Mindy Park in SatCom.
我要紧急连线文森特·卡普尔
I need the emergency contact for Vincent Kapoor.
对, 他
Yes, him.
对, 紧急
Yes, it's an emergency.
- 有多确定? - 100%
- How sure? - A 100%
你扯淡呢吧?
You got to be shitting me?
安
妮
·
蒙
特
罗
斯
美
航
局
媒
体
关
系
部
长
证明给我看
Prove it to me.
首先
For a start.
天阳能板被清掉了
Solar panels have been cleaned.
可能是风刮走的
They could've been cleaned by wind.
回放
Back it up.
看火星车2号
Look at Rover 2.
根据记录, 路易斯指挥官把它开出来, 在第17太阳日
According to the logs, Command Lewis took it out, Sol 17,
插在居住舱充电
plugged it into the Hab to recharge.
它被挪动了
It's been moved.
她可能忘了把挪动记录下来了
She could have forgotten to log the move.
不, 不太可能
No. Not likely.
我们为什么不直接问路易斯
Why don't we just ask Lewis.
我们直接现在用飞船通讯问她呗
Let's get on CAPCOM and ask her directly right now.
不, 不, 如果沃特尼真的活着
No, no. If Watney is really alive,
我们不要让阿瑞斯3号成员知道
we don't want the ARES 3 crew to know.
你, 你怎么能不告诉他们?
How- How can you not tell them?
他们还有10个月的航程回家
They have another 10 months on their trip home.
太空旅行很危险, 他们需要警觉且不能分心
Space travel is dangerous, they need to be alert and undistracted.
但是, 他们已经以为他死了
But, they already think he's dead.
他们发现落下一个大活人肯定会不知所措
And they'd be devastated to find out they left him there alive.
抱歉, 不过你没有考虑周全
I'm sorry but you have not thought this through.
我是说, 我们, 我们要怎么说?
I mean, what- what are we going to say?
亲爱的美国, 还记得那个被我们弄死的了还办了特别好的葬礼的宇航员吗?
Dear America, remember that astronaut we killed and had a really nice funeral for?
结果是他还活着, 我们把他扔在火星了
Turns out he's alive, and we left him on Mars.
我们的锅, 真挚的美航局
Our bad, sincerely NASA.
我是说, 你意识到山雨欲来了吗?
I mean, do you realise the shit storm that's about to hit us?
我们该怎么对付公众
How're we going to handle the public.
法律上讲, 我们有24个小时来公布这些照片
Legally, we have 24 hours to release these pictures.
我们发表一份声明
We release a statement with them.
我们不希望要让人们自己去琢磨
We don't want people working it out on their own.
好的, 长官
Yes, sir.
听着, 如果我没算错, 他会在我们救到他之前
Look, if my math is right, he's going to starve to death
就会饿死
long before we can help him.
你无法想象他在那儿都经历着什么
You can't imagine what he is going through up there.
我是说, 他离家5000万英里远
I mean, he's 50 million miles away from home.
他以为孑然一身, 他以为我们放弃了
He thinks he's totally alone. He thinks we gave up on him.
这会让一个人怎样, 心理学上讲?
And what does that do to a man, psychologically?
他现在究竟在想什么呢?
What the hell is he thinking right now?
我一定会死在这儿
I'm definitely going to die out here.
只要我再听一首哥特嘻哈迪斯科
If I have to listen to anymore goth hop disco music.
天哪, 路易斯指挥官, 你就不能带一些这个世纪的东西吗?
My god, Commander Lewis, couldn't you have packed anything from this century?
不, 我不, 我不要再《舞力无限》了
No, I'm not. I'm not going to turn the beat around.
我拒绝
I refuse to.
你们已经尝试过用哪些方式和马克·沃特尼联系?
What attempts have been made to make contact with Mark Watney?
我们正在努力
We're working on it.
他有充足的供给来求生吗?
Does he have enough supplies to survive?
我们会调查清楚
We'll be looking into that.
这对贵局有什么影响? 您是否准备辞职?
What does this say about the agency? Are you going to resign?
不
No.
桑德斯博士......
Dr. Sanders...
是时候想长远一些了
It's time to start thinking long term.
美航局的下一个任务是阿瑞斯4号
The next NASA mission is ARES 4
它应该在斯基亚帕雷利陨石坑登陆
and it's suppose to land at Schiaparelli crater,
3200公里远
3200 km away.
三千
两百公里
hundred kilometers.
4年后, 阿瑞斯小队来的时候
In 4 years, when the next ARES crew arrives,
我得在这儿
I'll have to be there.
也就是说我得去陨石坑
Which means I have to get to the crater.
好吧, 那么问题来了
Okay, so here's the rub.
我有1台能用的火星车, 设计最大里程为25公里
I've got 1 working Rover, designed to go a max distance 35 km.
使用之前电池要在居住舱充电
Before the battery has to be recharge at the Hab.
这是问题一
That's problem A.
问题二, 完整走这一趟要花掉我大约50天
Problem B, is this journey is going to take me roughly 50 days to complete.
所以, 我得活50天下来
So, I got to live for 50 days
火星车里有个微型生命维持装置, 有微型面包车那么大
inside a Rover with marginal life support, the size of a small van.
所以
So.
在这种悲催情况下, 我只剩下一个选择
In the face of overwhelming odds, I'm left with only 1 option.
我得搞搞科研把这破事儿解决了
I'm going to have to science the shit out of this.
好, 所以, 成功了
Okay. So, a success.
通过搜刮1号车, 我把电量增加了一倍
I've double battery life, by scavenging Rover 1.
但是, 如果我使用加热器
But, if I use the heater,
每天就会耗掉一半的电量
I will burn through half of my battery every day.
如果我不用加热器, 我就会......
If I do not use my heater, I will be...
被热力学定律慢慢杀死
slowly killed by the laws of Thermodynamics.
我很想现在就把问题解决了, 不过......
I would love to solve this problem right now, but...
不巧, 我的蛋蛋都冻僵了
unfortunately, my balls are frozen.
不行了, 就这样吧, 就这样吧
I can't. I'm calling it. I'm calling it.
好消息是, 我可能有办法解决我的取暖问题了
Good news, I may have a solution to my heating problem.
坏消息是, 那我就必须把放射性同位素温差发电器挖出来
Bad news, it involves me digging up the radioisotope thermoelectric generator.
如果我还记得没错, 训练时其中一课的名字就是
Now, if I remember my training correctly, One of the lessons was titled:
不要把那个大钚盒子挖出来, 马克
Don't dig up the big box of plutonium, Mark.
我明白, 同位素电池对宇宙飞船来说是好东西, 但如果在人类身边裂了
I get it, RTGs are good for spacecraft, But if they rupture around humans,
那人就死翘翘了
no more humans.
这就是为什么我们到这儿就把它埋了起来
Which is why buried it when we arrived.
还插了个旗子
And planted that flag,
这样我们就不会蠢到不小心又和它亲密接触
so we can never be stupid enough to accidentally go near it again.
不过, 只要我不打破它
But, as long as I don't break it,
工程后勤部大声说了：“毛事儿都没有”
Elmo did said 'Everything will be fine.', out loud.
听我说, 关键就是, 我再也不冷了
Look, the point is, I'm not cold anymore.
当然, 我也可以想成, 其实
And sure, I could choose to think about the fact that I'm...
我很暖和是因为我身后有跟着一个正在衰变的放射性同位素
warm because I have a decaying radioactive isotope riding right behind me,
但现在我手头有更大的问题
But right now I got bigger problems on my hands.
我把路易斯指挥官个人硬盘的每一个文件都翻了一遍
I've showered every single data file on Commander Lewis personal drive.
这真真儿是她最不迪斯科的歌了
This is officially the least disco song she owns.
沃特尼要去哪儿?
Where is Watney going?
这个, 我们认为他在准备一个行程
Well, we think he is preparing for a journey.
他在进行定量的测试
He's been conducting equal amount of test .
开着2号火星车一次比一次远
Taking the Rover 2 out for longer and longer trips each time.
去哪儿?为什么他不待在相对安全的居住舱?
To what end? Why would he leave relative safety of the Hab?
嗯, 我们认为他打算去阿瑞斯4号发射点
Well, we think he plans to travel to the Ares 4 launch site
从而与我们取得联系, 不过这会很冒险
in order to make contact with us, but it would be a dangerous gamble.
但如果我们能和他对话, 我们会告诉他留在原地
But, if we could talk to him, we would tell him to stay put
并相信我们会竭力带他活着回家
And to trust that we're doing everything in our power to bring him home alive.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
不要说“带他活着回家”, 文森特
Don't say 'Bring him home alive', Vincent.
你知道吗, 这些采访一点也不轻松
You know what, these interviews aren't easy.
但愿没有问题, 我都尽可能说得正面积极了
God forbid, I try to say something proactive and positive.
安妮!安妮!
不再让文森特上电视了, 收到
No more Vincent on TV. Copy that.
76千米, 我没看错吧?
76 kilometers. Am I reading that right?
您在问我吗?
Are you asking me?
是的
I am.
是, 长官
Yes, sir.
马克从居住舱径直向外开了2个小时车
Mark drove 2 hours straight away from the Hab,
短暂下车活动, 然后又开了2小时
Did a short EVA and then drove for another 2.
我们认为下车活动是换电池
We think the EVA was to change batteries.
他没载着充氧器或者再生水装置?
He didn't load up the oxygenator or the water reclaimer?
每41个小时会有17分钟的间隔
Every 41 hours, there is a 17 minute gap.
轨道运动就会这样, 所以......
It's just the way the orbits works, so...
我们有可能漏掉了什么
it's possible that we missed something.
我要间隔降到4分钟
I want that gap down to 4 minutes.
我会给你全部权限来管理卫星以及调整轨道
I'm giving you total authority over satellite trajectories and orbital adjustments.
实现它
Make it happen.
好的
Okay.
咱们假设帕克小姐没有漏掉什么
Let's assume Ms. Park didn't miss anything,
所以, 马克没有前往阿瑞斯4号, 暂且
So, Mark is not going to Ares 4, yet,
但他很聪明, 明白了这是他惟一的机会
But he's smart enough to figure out that is his only chance.
布鲁斯, 我们的先行补给最早能什么时候到达?
Bruce, what's the earliest we can get a pre- supply there?
这个嘛, 鉴于地球和火星之间的距离
Well, with the positions of the Earth and Mars,
要用9个月
It'll take 9 months.
而且要先用6个月来建造装置
And it'll takes 6 months to build them in the first place.
3个月
3 months.
3?
你会说这不可能, 然后我会发表一个讲话
You're going to say it's impossible, and then I'm going to make a speech
讲讲你们实验室成员的杰出能力
about the blinding capabilities of the JPL team,
然后你们就会在脑子里算算数, 说一些话
And then you're going to do the math in your head, And say something
比如：“一个人加班会很可怕”
like, "The overtime alone would be a nightmare."
一个人加班会很可怕
The overtime alone would be a nightmare.
开工吧, 我会想办法给你们酬劳的
Get started. I'll find you the money.
我们得告诉小队
We need to tell the crew.
- 米契, 我们讨论过了 - 不, 是你在讨论
- Mitch, we've discussed this. - No, you discussed this.
我才是决定怎样对小队最好的人
I'm the one who decides what's best for the crew.
他们理应知道
They deserve to know.
一旦有实际的救援方案, 我们就告诉他们
Once there's a real rescue plan, we'll tell them.
否则, 待议
Otherwise, it's moot.
布鲁斯有3个月来把装备搞定
Bruce has 3 months to get the payload done.
这才是现在的重点
That's all that matters right now.
我们会尽力的
We will do our best.
你不尽力马克就死了
Mark dies if you don't.
这些土豆我已经种了48太阳日了, 所以......
It's been 48 Sols since I planted the potatoes, so...
现在该收获、种新的了
Now it's time to reap and re- sow.
它们长得比我想的还好
They grew even better than I expected.
我现在有400株健康土豆
I now have 400 healthy potato plants.
我小心地把它们挖出来以免伤到植株
I dug them up being careful to leave their plants alive.
小的用来播种, 大的成了我的盘中餐
The smaller ones are reseed, the larger ones are my food supply.
纯天然、有机、火星培育土豆
All natural, organic, Martian grown potatoes.
你可不是天天能见到的, 不是么?
You don't hear that everyday, do you?
话说, 这些都毫不重要
And by the way, none of this matter at all
如果我想不出办法联系美航局的话
If I can't figure out a way to make contact with NASA.
我知道该做什么了
I know what I'm going to do.
哦, 他又移动了
Oh, he's moving again.
他到底要去哪儿?
Where the hell is he going?
他13天没有新动作了
He hasn't change course for 13 days.
他离阿瑞斯4号一点儿都不近
He's no where near the Ares 4.
问题是他都没有定向的路线
Problem is he's not taking a direct route.
我是说, 他可能在试图绕过一些障碍
I mean, he might be trying to avoid some obstacle.
什么障碍?
What obstacle?
那可是阿西达里亚平原, 一片不毛之地除了......
It's Acidalia Planitia. There is nothing out there except the...
啥?
What?
我需要地图
I need a map.
好
Yeah.
嘿, 别闹, 哥们儿, 你干嘛呢?
Hey. Come on, man. What's are you doing?
没事, 没事, 我能借用一下吗?
It's alright. It's alright. Can I borrow this?
好, 那么, 居住舱在哪儿?
Okay. So, where's the Hab location?
北纬31.2º, 西经28.5º
31.2° north, 28.5° West.
好, 那, 沃特尼在哪儿?
Okay. And, where is Watney?
这儿
Here.
好, 好
Okay, okay.
好了, 我知道他要去哪儿了
Okay. I know where he's going.
我要去坐飞机
I need to get on an airplane.
你好, 请跟我来
Hi. Please follow me.
- 你好吗, 文森特? - 布鲁斯
- How are you, Vincent? - Bruce.
航程愉快吗?
Good flight?
是啊
Yeah.
在仓库里, 就在转角
It's in storage, just around the corner.
文森特, 很高兴见到你
Vincent, nice to see you.
很高兴见到你
Nice to see you.
马克有多大几率能让它恢复运转?
What are the chances of Mark to get it working again?
不好说, 1997年就跟我们失联了
It's hard to say. We lost contact in 1997.
我们认为是电池不行了
We think it was battery failure.
但我要指出, 它已经比预期多坚持了3倍的时间
But I like to point out, it last 3 times longer than we expected.
不是要批评你们实验室的作品
Nobody is criticizing JPL's work
我只想和所有97年就在这儿的人聊一聊
I just need to speak with everybody who was here in 97.
别急, 他们来了, 大伙儿
Don't worry, they're here. Guys.
我想介绍一下, 文森特·卡普尔, 美航局火星任务总指挥
I would like to introduce, Vincent Kapoor, Director of the Mars missions, NASA.
这是我们现在的队伍
This is our current team,
- 还有原先工程的人员 - 怎么样?你好吗?
- and original project members. - How ya doing? Alright?
- 这是那个复制品? - 就是它
- Is this the replica? - This is her.
好, 咱们看看
Okay. Let's see it.
探路者
Pathfinder.
拜托, 拜托
Come on. Come on.
日了狗了, 好吧
Holy shit. Okay.
无线电状态, 正在采集遥测信号
Broadcasting Status. Listening for telemetry signal.
好吧, 收到信号
Okay. Signal acquired.
- 好啊 - 好吧
- Alright. - Okay.
摄像头
Camera.
来了
Incoming.
你收到了吗?
Are you receiving me?
是, 否
Yes. No.
好, 让摄像头指向“是”
Okay. Point the camera, yes.
消息来回要32分钟
32 minutes round trip communication time.
他只能问是不是的问题
All he can do is ask, yes, no, questions.
我们只能转摄像头
All we can do is to point the camera.
这可能不会像咱们围坐一桌对答如流那样
This won't be exactly what we might have gone, when we're around the table and snap your repartee
- 你在逗我吗? - 蒂姆, 蒂姆
- Are you kidding me? - Tim. Tim.
- 转摄像头别废话 - 收到
- Just point the camera. - Roger that.
转动摄像头
Pointing the camera.
是!
Yes!
那么, 问题就是
So, here's the rub.
有时候, 我们总要进行复杂的天体物理工程学交流
Somehow, we have to have complex astrophysical engineering conversations .
只能通过一个静止画面摄像头, 还是1996年产的
Using nothing but a still frame camera, from 1996.
好在
Luckily
摄像头会转
The camera does spin.
所以, 我可以做个字母表
So, I can make an alphabet.
不能是我们的字母表
It can't be our alphabet.
26个字母加上问题牌子除360度, 每个就13度角
26 characters plus a question card and a 360 gives us 13 degrees of arc.
这太窄了, 我永远也没法知道摄像头在指哪个
That's way too narrow. I'll never know where the camera is pointing at.
十六进制
Hexadecimal.
十六进制带我飞
Hexadecimal to the rescue.
我记得你们其中一位老是把一张ASCII表到处乱丢
I figured one of you guys who kept an ASCII table lying around,
我是对的
I was right.
女士们先生们, 请看超级程序猿, 贝斯·约翰森
Ladies and Gentlemen, I give you Super nerd, Beth Johanssen.
她还有《魔域2》
Who also have copies of Zork II
还有《火卫一的皮衣女神》, 就在她笔记本电脑上
and Leather Goddesses of Phobos on her personal laptop.
认真的, 约翰森
Seriously, Johanssen.
谁想到弄这么个“孤独博物馆”的, 队长你吗?
Who thought the smithsonian of loneliness, captain ya?
我不是发牢骚
Not that I'm complaining.
好!我又凭什么谈孤独呢?
Yes! Who am I to talk about loneliness?
我知道他这是干嘛
I know where he's going with this.
好的
Alright
FO
F, O.
7W
7, W.
文森特, 文森特
Vincent. Vincent.
醒醒
Wake up.
现在我们可以进行更复杂的对话了
Now that we can have more complicated conversations,
美航局的那群聪明人给我发过黑掉火星车的教程
The smart people at NASA have sent me instructions on how to hack a Rover
这样它就能跟探路者对话
so that it can talk to Pathfinder.
如果我把它黑了, 就一小段代码, 只需修改20下
If I hack, a tiny bit of code, just 20 instructions
火星车的操作系统
in the Rover's operating system,
美航局就能把火星车连在探路者的无线电频率上
NASA can link the Rover to Pathfinder's broadcasting frequency
我们就能运作起来
and we're in business.
马克
Mark,
我是文森特·卡普尔
this is Vincent Kapoor.
我们从第54太阳日就开始关注你
We've been watching you since SOL54.
整个世界都在支持着你
The whole world is rooting for you.
找探路者这招干得漂亮
Amazing job, getting Pathfinder.
我们在努力制订救援计划
We're working on rescue plans.
同时, 我们在筹备一个补给任务
Meantime, we're putting together a supply mission
保证你吃饱穿暖, 直到阿瑞斯4号到达
to keep you fed until Ares 4 arrives.
喜接来函
Glad to hear it.
好的
Okay.
喜接来函很期待能活下去
Glad to hear it. Really looking forward to not dying.
- 哦 - 嚄
- Oh. - Whoa.
好啊
Yeah.
小队怎样了?
How's the crew?
他们得知我还活着时说了什么?
What did they say when they found out I was alive?
大伙儿, 我们能单独待会儿吗, 拜托
Guys, can we get some space, please.
- 我? - 对, 你
- Me? - Yeah, you.
就给我一点时间
Just give me a second.
你该告诉他
You should tell him.
我们还没告诉小队你还活着
We haven't told the crew you are alive yet.
我们得让他们专心在任务上
We need them to concentrate on the mission.
啥?
(What?)
我操!
(What the fuck!)
我了个大操!
他说
He says.
他们不知道我活着?
They don't know I'm alive?
我了个大和谐
What the F word.
和谐ing, 再和谐, 你们什么毛病?
F word in gerund form. F word again, what's wrong with you?
马克, 请注意用辞
Mark, please watch your language.
你输入的所有内容都在全球直播
Everything you type is being broadcast live all over the world.
是嘛?
Yeah?
哦, 天了噜
Oh, my God.
是的, 先生, 他现在极其紧张
Yes, sir. He's under a tremendous amount of stress.
我明白, 我们在努力
I understand. We're working on it.
我肯定他不是他说的话的意思
I'm sure he didn't mean what he said.
谢谢您, 总统先生
Thank you, Mr. President.
问题是, 马克说得对
Problem is, Mark's right.
我们越是拖着, 事态就越严重
The longer we wait, The worse it's going to get.
我们得告诉小队
We need to tell the crew.
你要在文森特人在帕萨迪纳的时候提出来
You're bringing this up while Vincent is in Pasadena
这样他在那边也没法跟你撕逼
so he can't argue the other side.
我才不必理会文森特
I shouldn't have to answer to Vincent.
或者别的任何人
Or anyone else.
是时候了, 泰迪
It's time, Teddy.
路易斯指挥官?
Commander Lewis?
说
Go ahead.
数据转移差不多完成了
Data dump is almost complete.
收到, 我来了
Copy that. On my way.
你挺忙啊
You're in a hurry.
是啊, 我儿子昨天3岁了
Yeah. My son turned 3 yesterday.
应该是聚会的照片
Should be pictures of the party.
收到一堆私人信息, 正在发到你的笔记本电脑上
Got a batch of personals. Dispatching them to your laptop now.
我可不想看, 沃格尔, 诡异的德国迷信电子邮件
I don't mean to read, Vogel, weird German fetish e- mails.
遥测信息更新了
The telemetry updates.
嘿, 不管是啥都是发给你的, 大哥
Hey, whatever does it for you, man.
哦, 有个视频信息是, 是发给全队的
Oh, there's a video message. It's- It's address to the whole crew.
播放来一下, 各位
Play it. Come on, guys.
我来掺合一下遥测活动
I want to get in on that telemetry action.
嗨, 你们好, 我是米契, 米契·亨德逊
Hi, hello. It's Mitch, Mitch Henderson.
我有一些消息
I have some news.
这是没法卖关子的
There's no subtle way to put this.
马克·沃特尼还活着
Mark Watney is still alive.
哦天哪
Oh my God.
我知道这是个惊喜, 我知道你们会有很多疑问
I know that's a surprise, I know you'll have lots of questions,
不过, 下面是些基本情况
But here are the basics.
他活着, 而且健康
He's alive and he's healthy.
我们......我们2个月前发现的......决定不告诉你们
We... We found out 2 months ago and... decided not to tell you.
- 什么? - 2个月?
- What? - 2 months?
哦天哪
Oh my god.
我当时强烈反对那个决定
I was strongly against that decision.
我们现在告诉你们, 是因为......
We are telling you now, because...
我们终于跟他取得联系
we finally have communication with him.
也有了可行的救援方案
and a viable rescue plan.
我们会给你们发一篇关于所发生的事的报告, 完整全面的报告
We'll get you a write up of what happened. A full write up of everything.
但不是你们的错
But it's not your fault.
马克每次发消息都会强调这一点
Mark stresses that everytime it comes up.
那么......是啊
So... Yeah.
花点时间消化一下
Take some time to absorb this.
并且......把所有想问的都发过来, 我们会回答
And... send all the questions you want, we'll answer.
好了, 亨德逊挂断
Alright, Henderson out.
卧槽, 他活着
Holy shit. He's alive.
我把他丢下了
I left him behind.
- 不 - 不
- No. - No.
我们都把他丢下了
We all left together.
你们是在听从命令
You were following orders.
我把他丢下了
I left him behind.
所以, 现在美航局可以跟我对话, 他们不会住嘴
So, now that NASA can talk to me, they won't shut up.
他们想给居住舱的每个系统都不停升级
They want constant updates on every Hab system,
他们还有满满一屋子人尽可能微观管理我的庄稼
and they've a room full of people trying to micromanage my crops.
可真是棒啊
Which is awesome.
听着, 我是说, 我不是想表现得自大什么的
Look, I mean, I don't mean to sound arrogant or anything,
但我可是这个星球上最伟大的植物学家, 所以......
But I am the greatest botanist on this planet, so...
哦, 跟美航局对话的又一个大好处
Oh, one big bonus to this communication with NASA again
就是电邮, 我又能收到了
is the e- mail, I'm getting them again.
好大一次数据转移, 就像我在赫尔墨斯号上一样
A big data dump. It's like when I was on the Hermes.
我甚至收到了总统的一封
I even got one from the President.
现在最酷的是, 我收到最酷的一封是
The coolest one now. The coolest one I got
来自芝加哥大学的, 我的母校
was from the University of Chicago, where I Alma mater.
他们说, 一旦你在一个地方种植作物
They said that, once you grow crops somewhere,
你就正式地“殖民”了
You officially "colonized" it.
所以, 技术上讲
So, technically,
我殖民火星了
I colonized Mars.
来战啊, 尼尔·阿姆斯特朗
In your face, Neil Armstrong.
哦, 还有一个事儿, 有人请求
Oh, another news. There's been a request
我下次传消息的时候发一张照片
for me to post for a photograph on my next transmission.
我在苦苦思索我应该摆成高中生
I am trying to figure out whether I should go with high school senior,
还是婀娜纯洁少女
or coquettish ingenue.
不过, 我不太确定穿上宇航服是什么样
But, I'm not really sure how it's going to look with my spacesuit on.
噫
Ayeee.
他在干嘛?
What's he doing?
我要的是照片, 这啥, 他在学方兹吗?
I ask for a photo, and what, he's the Fonz?
只要感谢我们好歹给了你几张, 安妮
Just be grateful we got you something, Annie.
我不能用这个, 文森特, 你知道的
I can't use this, Vincent, and you know that.
我需要他的脸的照片
I need a picture of his face.
嗯, 我可以告诉他把头罩摘下来
Well, I can tell him to take off his helmet,
但是接下来他…你懂的, 就挂了
But then he, you know, die.
所以
So.
我们会发布照片, 并详细描述救援程序
We'll release the photo and we'll detail the rescue operation.
我想宣布, 我们明年会发一些补给过去
I want to announce we're launching some supplies to him next year
通过霍曼转移窗口
during the Hohmann Transfer Window.
布鲁斯, 你的队伍能赶上进度吗?
Bruce, your team still on schedule?
会很紧张, 不过我们能完成
It will be tight, but we'll make it.
9个月的行程, 也就是飞船会在第868太阳日到达火星
9 months travel time, that puts the probe to Mars on Sol 868.
我们拿到植物学队伍的分析了吗?
Did we get the Botany team's analysis?
是的, 他们估计马克的作物能坚持到第912太阳日
Yeah. They estimate Mark's crops will last till Sol 912.
他们委婉地承认了他, 他做得很不错
They grudgingly admit that he's- he's doing a great work.
委婉地?
Grudgingly?
这个, 是啊, 马克意图告诉他们和他们自己啪啪啪
Well, yeah. Mark has the tendency to tell them to have sex with themselves
只要每次他们质疑他的决定
whenever they question one of his decisions.
让他上线, 文森特, 我们再也受不了错误的沟通了
Get him online, Vincent. We can't afford any miscommunication.
我讨厌这样间不容发
I hate this margin.
912太阳日的食物, 我们在第868日到达
912 Sols worth of food, we get there in 868.
还是在万无一失的前提下
That's assuming nothing goes wrong.
啊!
Aw!
呃啊!
Aww!
检测到宇航服破损
SUIT BREACH DETECTED
氧气浓度：极低
OXYGEN LEVEL CRITICAL
氧气浓度：10%
OXYGEN LEVEL : 10%
氧气浓度：5%
OXYGEN LEVEL : 5%
宇航服压力：稳定
SUIT PRESSURE STABLE
压力：稳定
PRESSURE STABLE
完了!
GONE!
完了, 完了, 完了, 完了!
Gone, gone, gone, gone!
作物都死了
Crops are dead.
完全失压, 大部分水都沸腾掉了
Complete loss of pressure boiled off most of the water.
之前活下来的细菌都在零下温度中死掉了
Any bacteria that survived died in the subzero temperatures
暴露在火星的大气里就会这样
when exposed to Mar's atmosphere.
他有多长时间?
How long has he have?
哦, 他还可以吃现有的土豆, 只不过不能再种了, 所以......
Oh. He can still eat the potatoes he has, he just can't grow anymore, so...
他有......200太阳日
Give him... 200 Sols.
太空餐能吃多久?409太阳日?
Rations give him to what? Sol 409?
对, 加上土豆, 609日
So, with potatoes, 609.
所以, 到第868太阳日, 他都死透了
So, by Sol 868, he'll be long dead.
我们只能尽快发射
We're going to have to launch as soon as possible,
来改变航程时间
which changes our travel time.
是的, 我们正在研究
Yeah, we're working on it.
初步估计需要414天的航程
Preliminary estimates call for a 414 day trip.
现在是第135太阳日
It's Sol 135 now.
我们需要13天来搭建助推器, 进行检查
We need 13 days to mount the boosters, perform inspections
也就是布鲁斯和他的团队
which gives Bruce and his team
有47天来做飞行器
47 days to make this probe.
我会让你和布鲁斯通话, 把消息告诉他
I'll let you call Bruce. Give him the news.
好吧
Okay.
我......我得去换一下衣服
I'm...  I'm going to need a change of clothes.
亲爱的马克
Dear Mark,
显然, 美航局现在允许我们和你对话了
Apparently, NASA's letting us talk to you now.
而我, 抽到了下下签
And I, drew the short straw.
抱歉我们把你扔在了火星
Sorry we left you behind on Mars,
但是我们就是不喜欢你
but we just don't like you.
还有, 赫尔墨斯号少了你之后宽敞多了
Also, it's a lot roomier on the Hermes without you.
我们得轮流做你的工作
We have to take turns doing your tasks,
不过, 我是说, 就是种地嘛
but, I mean, it's only botany.
算不上是科学
It's not real science.
哦, 天哪
Oh, Jesus.
火星怎么样?
How's Mars?
亲爱的马丁内斯, 火星挺好
Dear Martinez, Mars is fine.
我不小心把居住舱给炸了
I accidentally blew up the Hab,
但不幸的是, 路易斯指挥官所有的迪斯科音乐都逃过一劫
but unfortunately all of Commander Lewis' disco music still survived.
每天我都出去走走, 看看广袤的地平线
Every day I go outside and look at the vast horizons.
只是因为我可以
Just because I can.
代我向其他人问好
Tell the others I said hello.
会的, 哥们儿
Will do, buddy.
压力：稳定
PRESSURE STABLE.
5, 10
5, 10,
15, 20, 30, 35
15, 20, 30, 35,
40.
52.
里奇
Rich.
醒醒
Wake up.
抱歉, 但他们在问飞行器的情况
Sorry, but they're asking for the probe courses.
几点了?
What time is it?
大概......3:42
It's about... 03:42
我知道情况越来越糟
I know we're coming at this backwards,
但是我们不能定下一个有太多未知因素的发射日期
but we can't commit to a firm launch date with so many unknowns.
还好
It's alright.
全部25种发射模型都是414天到火星
All 25 models for launch will take 414 days to reach the Mars.
他们在推进时间上差别很小
They varies slightly in thrust duration and
燃料消耗也几乎相等
fuel requirement is nearly as identical.
不是很好的发射时间, 是吧?
Not a good time to launch, is it?
是啊, 地球和火星的位置真的很不利
Yeah. Earth and Mars are really badly positioned.
真是, 差点儿就能更容易, 只要......
Heck, it'd almost be easier if you...
差点儿就能更容易什么?
Almost easier to what?
我要再喝点咖啡
I need more coffee.
- 你没事吧? - 没事
- Are you alright? - It's fine.
差点儿就能更容易啥啊?
Almost easier to what?
你知道我是你上司, 是吧?
You do understand I'm your boss, right?
嗯哼
Uh- huh.
我们来问个非常非常昂贵的问题
Let's ask the very very expensive question.
飞行器能按时就绪吗?
Is the probe going to be ready on time?
- 我们落后了 - 给我个数字
- We are behind. - Give me a number.
15天, 15天我就能完成
15 days. 15 days and I can get it done.
好, 就定下15天13天的时候搭建飞行器
Alright, let's create 15 days. 13 days to mount the probe.
可以提前吗?
Can we reduce?
其实搭建飞行器要3天
It actually takes 3 days to mount the probe.
但我们可以压缩到2天, 是吧?
And we can get it down to 2, right?
我可以压缩到2天
I can get it down to 2.
10天的时间用来检查和测试
10 days are for tests and inspections.
十次检查有几次能发现问题?
How often do those inspections reveal a problem?
你的意思是我们不检查了?
Are you suggesting we don't do the inspections?
现在, 我问的是十次检查有几次能发现问题?
Right now, I'm asking how often they reveal a problem?
半次
1 in 20.
但检查正是倒计时会中止的原因
But that's grounds for countdown halt.
我们不能冒这个险
We can't take that chance.
还有谁有更安全的方法来争取更多时间吗?
Anyone else know a safer way to buy more time?
凯勒博士, 让沃特尼节衣缩食多挺4天
Dr. Keller, stretch Watney's rations 4 more days.
他不会乐意, 但我们就可以凑出15天
He's not going to like it, but that will get us to 15.
- 而且我们要取消检查 - 泰迪
- And we'll cancel the inspections. - Teddy.
- 长官, 一旦出了事儿 - 责任在我
- Sir, If that ever got out. - It's on me.
你们有2周时间
You got your 2 weeks.
把活干完!
Get it done!
所以, 现在, 我得撑到飞行器把更多食物带来
So, now, I have to hold out until the probe gets here with more food.
你想看看最低卡路里是什么概念吗?
You want to see what minimum calorie count looks like?
标准节食方案
Standard issue ration.
现在不是每1天吃3个
But instead of 3 of these every 1 day,
而是每3天吃1个
I'm now eating 1 of these every 3 days.
现在他们要求我......
And now they've asked me...
这么做
to do that.
问题是
The point is,
多节食4天
stretch the rations 4 more days.
真是蛋疼
These are real dick punch.
我......
I'm...
我要用这个土豆蘸维生素片吃
I'm going to dip this potato in some crashed vitacarn.
谁也拦不了我
And there's nobody who can stop me.
我已经7天没有番茄酱了
It has been 7 days since I ran out of ketchup.
抬, 抬, 抬
Up. Up, up.
放这儿
Come up here.
我是航行指挥员, 马上开始检查发射状态
This is the Flight Director. Soon begin launch status check.
收到, 指挥开始检查发射状态
Roger that, Flight. Beginning launch status check.
你信上帝吗, 文森特?
Do you believe in god, Vincent?
是啊
Yeah.
这个, 我爸在印度的时候, 我妈是个施洗者, 所以, 是啊
Well. My father was a Hindu, My mother's a Baptist, so, yeah.
我信好几个神
I believe in several.
我们会接受任何援手
We'll take all the help we can get.
发射状态检查完毕
Launch status check complete.
我是指挥
This is Flight.
我们准备发射
We are go for launch.
开始倒计时
Proceed with the count.
10.
9, 8
9, 8,
7, 6
7, 6,
主引擎启动
Main engines start.
4, 3
4, 3,
- 2 - 点火
- 2, - Ignition.
1.
发射
Liftoff.
推进成功
Good thrust.
状态正常
Performance is normal.
火箭反馈数据正常
The payload is giving good data.
它现在安若磐石, 指挥推力矢量控制表现正常
She's rock solid at this point, Flight. TVC looks good.
- 天啊 - 好!
- My god. - Yes!
- 哟呼! - 耶
- Yoo hoo! - Yeah.
交通数据收集系统还要再工作一段时间
We have an extra TDCS duration.
好像有点异常振动, 指挥
We're getting a little shimmy, Flight.
再说一遍?
Say again?
火箭发生了剧烈的进动
We're getting a very large precession.
还好不?
Are we good?
指挥, 到临界值了
Flight, it's hitting the red line.
绕长轴17º的进动
Spinning on the long axis with a 17° precession.
发射指挥, 什么情况?
Launch, what's happening?
伊里斯受力为7个重力
Force on Iris is at 7 g's.
我们已经没有飞行器的读数了, 指挥
We've lost the readings on the probe, Flight.
- 哦 - 哦!
- Oh. - Oh!
- 哦, 天哪 - 天哪
- Oh, Jesus Christ. - Jesus.
它解体了, 指挥
We lost it, Flight.
卫星通讯?
SatCom?
没有卫星接收到信号
No satellite acquisition of signal.
失联
LOS.
这儿也失联了
LOS here too.
美国驱逐舰, 斯托克顿, 报告有碎片从天而落
US Destroyer, Stockton, Reporting debris falling from the sky.
发射控制中心所有人保持原位
Everyone in the LCC maintain your positions.
地面控制中心, 锁上门
GC. Lock the doors.
路易斯指挥官
Commander Lewis,
我可能需要你为我做些事情
I may need you to do something for me.
如果我死了, 我需要你去拜访一下我父母
If I die, I need you to check in with my parents.
他们会愿意听到我们在火星时的一切
They will want to hear all about our time here on Mars.
我知道这是强人所难
I know that sucks,
很难去跟一对夫妇谈论
and it will be hard talking to a couple
他们死去的儿子
about their dead son.
有太多要问
It's a lot to ask.
所以我才拜托你
Which is why I'm asking you.
我没有放弃
I'm not giving up.
我只是需要为每种结果做准备
I just need to prepare for every outcome.
请告诉他们
Please tell them.
告诉他们我爱我的工作
Tell them I love what I do,
而且我真的很擅长
And I'm really good at it.
而且我的牺牲
And I'm dying
是为了大事
for something big
美好的
and beautiful,
比我更伟大的事
and greater than me.
告诉他们, 我说了我能接受
Tell them I said I can live with that.
还要告诉他们
And tell them,
谢谢你们做我的爸爸妈妈
thank you for being my mom and dad.
中
国
家
航
天
局
北
京
我们用蛋白块换掉了标准口粮
We substituted protein cubes with the standard rations.
发射推进同时有横向的振动
The thrust of the launch combine with the simultaneous lateral vibration
熔化了蛋白块, 导致载重不均
liquified the cubes and created an imbalance load.
文森特, 这不应该在检查阶段就能发现吗?
Vincent, why wasn't this address from the inspection phase?
为了赶发射窗口, 我们只得加速进程
In order to make our launch window, we were forced to accelerate our schedule.
他们的宇航员这样会饿死
Their astronaut is going to die from hunger.
郭
明
首
席
科
学
家
国
航
局
当然, 还有其他办法
Of course. There are other ways.
朱
涛
副
首
席
科
学
家
国
航
局
太阳神的助推器, 我们的工程师检查过数据
Our engineers have ran the numbers of the Taiyang Shen's boosters.
它的容量可以到达火星的轨道
It has the fuel capacity to reach Mars orbit.
美航局为什么没有找我们?
Why didn't NASA approach us?
因为他们不知道
Because they don't know.
我们的数据是绝密的
Our data is classified information.
也就是说
That's to say.
假如我们什么都不做
If we do nothing...
世界将永远不会知道, 其实我们是可以帮得上忙的
The world will never knew, actually we could have helped.
那么, 仅仅是为了论证
So. For the sake of argument,
如果我们决定帮助他们
let's say we decided to help them.
我们把助推器给了他们, 也就是取消了太阳神计划
We give them the boosters, that means the cancellation of Taiyang Shen's program.
那我们, 就从航天的角度解决问题
Then let us, from Aerospace point of view, try to solve this problem.
寻求合作
Find a way to cooperate.
是
Yes.
是, 我明白
Yes, I understand.
谢谢
Thank you.
太好了!
Yes!
好了
Alright!
多亏我在中国的叔叔汤米, 我们可以再来一发
Thanks to my uncle Tommy in China, We got another chance at this.
现在我们用了62天完成伊里斯飞行器
Now we finished the Iris probe in 62 days,
我们如今要在28天里完成它
we're now going to attempt to finish it in 28.
我们可以抛掉所有着陆设备
We can jettison any kind of landing systems.
我们只送补给, 我们可以撞在火星上
We're sending only rations. We can crash land on Mars.
你应该挂掉电话
You should hang up the phone.
- 抱歉, 你谁啊? - 我叫里奇·珀内尔
- I'm sorry, who are you? - My name is Rich Purnell.
我在天文动力学部门工作, 你应该挂电话了, 就现在
I work in Astrodynamics, and you should hang up the phone, right now.
好吧, 好吧
Alright. Alright.
我回头打给你
I'm going to call you back.
我知道怎么救马克·沃特尼
I know how to save Mark Watney.
你的飞行器计划不会成功, 太多地方会出问题
Your probe plan won't work. Too many things can go wrong.
我有上策
I got a better way.
- 天文动力学? - 是啊
- Astrodynamics? - Yeah.
爱隆计划是什么鬼?
What the hell is Project Elrond?
我得亡羊补牢
I had to make something up.
但是, 爱隆?
But, Elrond?
因为这是个秘密会议
Because it's a secret meeting.
你怎么知道的?为什么爱隆的意思是秘密会议?
How do you know that? Why does Elrond mean secret meeting?
爱隆的会议, 来自《指环王》
The Council of Elrond. It's from the "Lord Of The Rings."
- 在那个会议上他们 - 《指环王》
- It's the meeting where they - The Lord Of The Rings.
决定毁掉魔戒
decide to destroy the One ring.
如果我们要称之爱隆计划
If we are going to call something Project Elrond,
我要我的代号叫做格洛芬德尔
I would like my codename to be Glorfindel.
我讨厌你们每一个人
I hate everyone of you.
泰迪到现在都还一头雾水呢
Teddy doesn't even know about this yet.
抱歉, 你是谁?
I'm sorry. Who are you?
这是里奇·珀内尔, 天文动力学家
This is Rich Purnell, Astrodynamics.
把你刚才跟我说的告诉他们
Tell them what you just told me.
我可以让赫尔墨斯号在第561太阳日前回到火星
I can get the Hermes back to Mars by Sol 561.
怎么做?
How?
请问, 你可以帮个忙站到那里去吗?
Would you stand right there for me, please?
谢谢, 就那儿, 很好
Thanks. Right there, great.
麻烦您, 站在那儿?就那儿
And could you, stand right there? Right there.
好, 咱们假设这个订书机是赫尔墨斯号
Okay. Let's pretend that this stapler is the Hermes,
您是......
And you are...
抱歉, 您叫什么来着?
I'm sorry. What's your name again?
泰迪, 我是美航局局长
Teddy. I'm the director of NASA.
好, 泰迪, 你是地球
Cool. Teddy, you're Earth.
现在, 赫尔墨斯号正朝着你
And right now, the Hermes is heading towards you,
开始数月之久的减速被捕获之旅
starting it's months long deceleration intercept,
但反之, 我想提出的是
but instead, what I'm proposing is,
它现在开始加速, 保持速度, 甚至获得更多速度
It start accelerating immediately, to preserve velocity and gain even more.
我们不被地球捕获, 但我们足够靠近
We don't intercept with Earth at all, but we come close enough...
以借助重力调整路线
to get a gravity assist and adjust course.
我们这么做的同时
While we're doing that,
- 我们换上新的飞行器 - 太阳神
- we resupply with the probe. - The Taiyang Shen.
带上我们需要运送的所有补给
Pick up whatever provisions we need.
我们就加速直奔火星而去了
And now we accelerating towards Mars.
你是火星
You're Mars.
现在, 我们速度太快没法落入轨道, 但是......
Now, we are going too fast at this point to fall into orbit, but...
我们可以经过定点
we can do a flyby.
经过定点有什么用, 如果你没法让沃特尼离开火星表面?
What good is a flyby if you can't get Watney off the surface?
沃特尼可以用微型飞行器拦截
Watney would intercept using  the MAV.
嗷
Ow.
然后我们就往家走
And then we just head home.
我做过计算了, 没问题的
I done the math. It checks out.
- 里奇 - 在, 长官
- Rich. - Yes, sir.
- 出去 - 好的
- Get out. - Alright.
- 他说得对吗? - 对
- Is he right? - Yep.
布鲁斯, 你怎么看?
Bruce, what do you think?
这个嘛, 听文森特的
Well, If Vincent say so.
- 我们得用太阳神 - 嗯哼
- We need to use the Taiyang Shen. - Uh- huh.
我, 我听漏什么了?为什么那么重要?
Wha- What am I missing? Why is that important?
因为我们要一击必中
Because we can only do one.
给沃特尼送去足够坚持到阿瑞斯4号的食物
Send Watney enough food to last till Ares 4,
和让赫尔墨斯号现在回去找他
or send Hermes back to get him right now.
两个计划都需要太阳神所以, 我们得二选一
Both plans require the Taiyang Shen. So, we have to choose.
但是, 赫尔墨斯号成员呢?
But, what about the Hermes' crew?
到时候得要求他们给他们的任务额外加上533天
It would be asking them, to add 533 extra days to their mission.
他们会毫不犹豫, 二话不说
And they wouldn't hesitate, not for a second.
赫尔墨斯号能超出计划任务运行533天吗?
Can the Hermes function for 533 days beyond the scheduled mission?
应该可以
Should.
按照完成整个阿瑞斯任务建造的
Built to last the full Ares mission.
所以, 技术上讲, 现在只走到了其寿命的一半
So, technically, it's only half way through it's lifespan.
- 不过, 如果出了问题 - 那么, 我们就会失去整个小队
- But, if something goes wrong. - Then, we lose the crew.
所以怎么办?我们要么冒高风险杀死一个人, 或者
So, what? We, either have a high chance of killing 1 person, or
冒低风险杀死6个人
low chance of killing 6 people.
我们怎么抉择?
How do we make that decision?
我们不用抉择, 布鲁斯
We don't have to make it, Bruce.
他来
He does.
是啊, 但是废话
Yeah. But, bullshit.
应该让路易斯指挥官来决定
Should be Commander Lewis' call.
我们仍有机会带5名宇航员安然回家
We still have a chance to bring 5 astronauts home safe and sound.
我不想用他们的生命冒险
I'm not risking their lives.
让他们来做决定
Let them make that decision.
米契, 我们不会采纳你的建议
Mitch, we're going with option 1.
你他妈就是个懦夫
You god damn coward.
- 约翰森? - 嗯
- Johanssen? - Yeah.
我知道现在是你的私人时间, 我可以打搅一下吗?
I know it's your private time. Can I bother you for a second?
好, 说吧
Yeah, go ahead.
- 你在哪儿? - 健身房
- Where are you? - The gym.
咋了?
What's up?
我刚收到我妻子的电邮, 主题是《我们的孩子》
I just got an e- mail from my wife, and the subject line says, "our children."
我的电脑打不开附件
My computer won't open the attachment.
好吧, 咱们看看
Okay. Let's take a look.
看看
Let's see.
这不是JPEG文件
This isn't a jpeg.
是, 是个纯ASCII文件
It's a- It's a plain ASCII text file.
我不太确定这是啥, 它......
I don't really know what we're looking at. It's...
你能看懂吗?
That make any sense to you?
里奇·珀内尔演算
Rich Purnell maneuver.
是对赫尔墨斯号航线的一种演算
It's a course maneuver for the Hermes.
天哪
My god.
211天之后任务就要以进入地球轨道告终了
The mission concludes with Earth intercept 211 days later.
能奏效吗?
Would it work?
我们计算过了, 能行
We ran the numbers. They checked out.
真是个了不得的任务
It's a brilliant course.
为啥搞得这么神秘?
So, why all the cloak and dagger?
因为这是直接违抗美航局的决定的
Because it goes directly against NASA's decision.
是啊, 如果我们执行这个任务, 他们必须给我们送补给, 要不我们就饿死了
Yeah. If we do the maneuver, they have to send the supply ship or we die.
我们可以强迫他们
We have the opportunity to force their hand.
我已我们怎么办?
So, are we going to do?
如果是我的决定, 我们现在就已经在路上了
If it's up to me, we'll already be on our way.
但就是你的决定啊, 难不成不是么?
But it is, no, isn't it? Up to you?
这次不是
Not this time.
这个任务可是美航局明确反对的
This is something NASA expressly rejected.
这可算是反叛, 我可不愿意直接被贯于这个名号
We're talking about mutiny here, which is not a word that I take lightly
所以, 我们要么一起, 要么什么都不干
So, we do this together, or not at all.
在你回答去不去之前, 想想后果
And, before you answer, consider the consequences.
如果我们在对接补给的时候没搞好, 我们都得死
If we mess up the supply rendezvous, we die.
如果我们没能好好的借助地心引力, 我们也是死
If we mess up the Earth gravity assist, we die.
如果我们每一环都做得完美
If we do everything perfectly,
我们还得在原本的任务上多加533 天
We add 533 days to our mission.
我们得在533天之后才能见到我们的家人
533 more days, before we see our families again.
在计划之外的533任务, 任何事情都可能发生
533 days of unplanned space travel where anything can go wrong.
如果任务出问题, 我们都回不去家
If it's mission critical, we die.
算上我
Sign me up.
好好好, 牛仔, 别急啊
Alright, cowboy, slow down.
你我都是军人
You and I, we're military.
我们回家以后有可能会被升职加薪
Chances are, we go home, they'll court martial us.
- 哦对哦, 还有这个呢 - 但对其他人来说,
- Oh yeah, there's that. - And for the rest of you guys,
我保证他们不会再把你们送到太空了
I guarantee they will never send you back up here again.
棒, 如果我们执行这个任务, 怎么搞?
Good. So, if we go for it, how would it work?
我来计划一下, 然后执行
I'll plot the course and execute it.
远程遥控
Remote override.
他们可以在地球上的总部控制赫尔墨斯号
They can take over the Hermes from Mission Control.
你能让他们控制不了么?
Can you disable it?
赫尔墨斯号有4个多余的飞行用电脑
Hermes has 4 redundant flight computers,
每一个都连接着3个通讯系统
each connected to 3 redundant comm systems.
我们不能把通信切断, 因为我们还需要遥感和指引
We can't shut down the comms, because we'll lose telemetry and guidance.
我们也不能把飞行用电脑关掉, 要不就不能操控飞船了
And we can't shut down the computers, because we need to run the ship.
我必须得人为禁止每个电脑上的远程操控系统
I'll have to disable remote override on each system.
这是它系统的一部分, 我得跳过这些代码
It's part of the OS, I have to jump over the code.
好, 所以用人话来说是什么意思?
Okay, but like in English, like what would that mean?
我能关掉远程遥控系统
I can do it.
牛逼
Great.
但我们必须意见一致
But, it has to be unanimous.
我们如果决定了, 那就要在宇宙中呆900多天
If we do this, it will be over 900 days of space.
这比任何人一辈子应该在宇宙中带的时间还要多, 所以
It's more than enough space for 1 life, so...
就这么做!
Yes.
我同意
I vote yes.
走, 咱去接他
Let's go get him.
约翰森?
Johanssen?
当然
Yes.
- 耶 - 耶!
- Yeah. - Yeah!
我们收到了一个赫尔墨斯号非计划中的状态提醒
Got an unscheduled status update from Hermes.
收到, 读出来
Roger, read it out.
这条信息说: “休斯顿, 请注意:
Message reads: 'Houston, please be advised:
里奇·珀内尔是一个目光坚定的火箭人
Rich Purnell is a steely- eyed missile man.'
什么鬼?
What?
飞行, 指示
Flight, Guidance.
赫尔墨斯号脱离了航线
Hermes is off course.
总部, 注意赫尔墨斯号脱离了航线 引导员, 准备一个校对方案
CAPCOM, advise Hermes they're drifting. Guidance, get a correction ready.
不对, 总部 不是一个航线漂移, 他们自己改变的航线
Negative, Flight. It's not adrift. They adjusted course.
什么鬼?
What the hell?
遥测部门, 有没有可能是设备故障?
Telemetry, any chance this is instrumentation failure?
没有, 控制总部
Negative, Flight.
引导员, 会计算一下他们偏离多久就改不回原来的航线了?
Guidance, work out how long they can stay on this course before it's irreversible?
正在计算, 总部
Working on that now, Flight.
谁是里奇·珀内尔?
Who's Rich Purnell?
我不清楚
I don't know.
快点有谁能他妈告诉我谁是里奇·珀内尔!
And somebody find out who the hell  Rich Purnell is!
安妮会在新闻发布会之前
Annie will go before the media this morning
告诉他们美航局决定让赫尔墨斯号更改航道回到火星
and inform them of NASA's decision to reroute the Hermes to Mars.
明智之举
Sounds like a smart move.
想想看后果
Considering the circumstances.
不管是谁给他们的这个任务调遣, 只是传递了以下信息而已
Whoever gave them the maneuver, only passed along information.
宇航员们自己做出了他们的决定
The crew made the decision on their own.
你可能就这样断送了他们的性命啊, Mitch
You may have killed them, Mitch.
我们利益共存
We're fighting the same war.
每次出事故, 大家都会忘记我们为什么要去太空旅行
Every time something goes wrong, the world forgets why we fly.
我只是想让咱们继续在空中飞着
I'm trying to keep us airborne.
远远比一个人的性命重要得多
It's bigger than 1 person.
不
No.
并不是这样
It's not.
等这件事情过去, 我等着你的辞职信
When this is over, I'll expect your resignation.
我明白了
I understand.
把我们的宇航员带回家吧
Bring our astronauts home.
第219太阳日
SOL 219
好的每个阿瑞斯任务都有三年期的任务前供给
Okay. Every Ares mission requires 3 years of pre- supplies.
所以美国航天局很久之前就决定了早一些送补给到火星
So NASA decided a long time ago it's a lot easier to
比带着补给飞过来要容易得多
send some of this stuff beforehand rather than bring it with us.
所以咯, 阿瑞斯4任务的飞行器
So, as a result, the MAV for Ares 4
已经在火星上面的, 在斯基阿帕雷利陨石坑, 等着我呢
is already there, at the Schiaparelli Crater, just waiting.
所以现在的计划就是我用它飞到火星轨道
So, the plan is for me to use that to go into orbit
正好当赫尔墨斯好经过,
just as the Hermes is passing,
然后在宇宙中
And I guess they catch me
接住我
in space.
然后, 我就得想想看怎么再度过200太阳日
So, I've got 200 Sols to figure out
然后带着所有能让我活命的东西过去：
how to take everything here that keeping me alive:
氧气供给, 水循环系统, 大气调节器
The oxygenator, the water reclaimer, the atmospheric regulator.
带着这么一大堆东西
Bring that all with me.
但是幸运的是我有全球最聪明的一帮人帮我
And luckily I have the- the greatest minds on planet Earth,
真的, 全球的聪明才智,
really, all of the brain power of the entire planet,
在帮我走出这个困境
helping me with this endeavor.
现在呢, 我们有了以下想法,
And so far they've come up with,
“嘿, 为啥不在你的探险车顶上钻孔呢
"Hey, why don't you drill holes in the roof of your Rover
然后用石头使劲敲他“
and hit it as hard as you can with a rock."
我觉得我们能达到目的地
We're going to get there.
第220太阳日
[SOL 220]
身份
Identification.
拜了火星
Goodbye Mars
再待533天?
533 days longer?
然后你同意了?
And you said yes to this?
你知道要是我被困住了, 他也会为了我这么做的
He would have done the same for me. You know that.
茄子
Cheese.
茄子茄子
Cheese. Cheese.
他是不是没说茄子, 他说了么?
He didn't do cheese. Did he do cheese?
嘿宝贝
Hey, baby.
- 嘿- 我为你准备了点东西
- Hey. - I got something for you.
我在一个跳蚤市场找到了这个
I found it in a flea market.
原版的
Original pressing.
骗人的吧
No. [ABBA GREATEST HITS]
跟新的一样
Not a scratch.
喜欢的不得了
I love it.
根据CNSA协议
With all due respect to your CNSA protocols ,
但- 但我们很久没有那么干了
but- but we haven't done things that way
从Apollo 9 之后
since- since... Apollo 9.
- 他懂了么? - （你听懂了么?）
- Did he get that? - (Do you understand?)
5.
4.
3.
2.
1. 点火
1. Ignition.
第227太阳日
[SOL 227]
7个月之后
7 MONTHS AFTER
第461太阳日
SOL 461
我一直在思考关于火星的法律部法规
I've thinking about laws on Mars.
有国际法说没有任何国家
There's an international treaty saying no country can lay claim
可以说地球以外的任何东西属于他们
to anything that is not on Earth.
另外一个跳跃又说了, 若你不在任何国土上,
And by another treaty,, if you're not in any countries territory,
就得遵循海上的法律
Maritime law applies.
所以火星应该算是”国际海域“
So, Mars is "international waters."
现在, NASA是美国非军事化的组织,
Now, NASA is an American nonmilitary organization,
科研站属于它
it owns the hab.
但是当我走出科研站, 我就在国际海域中了
But, the second I walk outside, I'm in international waters.
然后啊, 就有意思了
So, here's the cool part.
我现在正在前往斯基阿帕雷利陨石坑
I'm about to leave for the Schiaparelli crater
然后要征用阿瑞斯4的着陆器
where I'm going to commandeer the Ares 4 Lander.
没有人给我直接的指示去这么干,
Nobody explicitly gave me permission to this,
直到我登上阿瑞斯4 之前都不能给我任何指示
and they can't until I'm on board the Ares 4.
这样, 我就成了
So, that means I'm going to be
在国际海域未经许可的接管了一艘舰艇
taking over a craft over in international waters without permission.
这样, 根据定义, 就让我成为了一个海盗
Which, by definition, makes me a pirate.
- 马克·沃特尼, 宇宙海盗第461天
- Mark Watney, space pirate. [SOL 461]
系统关闭
systems shutdown
关闭完成
shutdown complete
宇宙海盗
Space pirate.
我管我去哪我都是第一个
Wherever I go, I'm the first.
真是一个奇妙的感觉
It's a strange feeling.
从探险车走出来,
Step outside the Rover,
第一人
first guy to be there.
爬那座上, 第一个那么做的人
Climb that hill, first guy to do that.
45亿年,
4.5 billion years,
从没人来过
nobody here.
今天, 我在这
And now, me.
我是第一个单独在一个星球上待着的男人
I'm the first person to be alone on an entire planet.
他怎么样?
How's he doing?
还不错
So far so good.
他在按着计划前行
He's... sticking to schedule.
在中午前4小时一直前进,
Directs for 4 hours before noon,
放好太阳能板, 等13小时让他们充好电,
Lays the solar panels, waits 13 hours for them to recharge,
这期间找个地方睡一觉, 然后重新开始
and sleeps somewhere in there and then, starts again.
有何进展啊?
How's he doing?
它让我们叫它, 大胡子船长
He asked us to call him, Captain Longbeard.
因为, 按理来说, 火星是隶属航洋法的
Well, technically, Mars would be under maritime laws.
我懂, 我懂他都跟我们解释过了
I know, I know. He explained it to us.
他在哪?
Where is he?
- 这- 好
- Here. - Okay.
这
Here.
好的
Okay.
第494太阳日
SOL 494
第517太阳日
SOL 517
我们要开门见山地说了,
Okay, we're going to start by stating,
你估计是不会喜欢我要告诉你的
for the record, that you're not going to like this.
哦, 真的么?
Oh, yeah?
是啊相遇速度有点问题
Yeah. The problem is the intercept velocity.
赫尔墨斯号不能进入火星的轨道
The Hermes. Well, they, it can't enter Mars orbit.
要不他们就没有足够的燃料回家了
Otherwise, they will never have enough fuel to, make it home.
飞行器只是为了到火星低位轨道设计的
The MAV was only designed to get to low Mars orbit.
所以想让马克完全脱离火星的引力,
So, in order for Mark to escape Mars gravity entirely,
然后和赫尔墨斯号相遇
and to intercept the Hermes...
- 他必须够快- 没错
- He has to be going fast. - Exactly.
就意味着我得让飞行器足够轻
Which means we need to make the MAV lighter.
比之前要轻5000公斤
A lot lighter. 5000 kg lighter.
但, 这是能做到的, 对吧?
But, you can do that, right?
能是能, 但是得耍些小手段
Well, there's some gimmes right off the bat.
设计是要带回500公斤的火星土壤和标本
The design presumes 500 kg of Martian soil and samples.
很明显我们不会那么做
Obviously we won't do that.
相对于6个宇航员, 我们现在只需要考虑一个人
And there's just 1 passenger instead of 6.
算上宇航服和装备, 又是500公斤?
With suits and gear, that's another 500?
扔了维持生命的设备 不需要这些
Ditch the support of life. We don't need it.
我们要让马克在整个过程中穿自己的宇航服
And I'm going to make Mark to wear his EVA suit for the whole trip.
等等!如果他穿着宇航服, 谁控制飞行器呢?
Wait a second! If he's in his EVA suit, How's he going to operate the controls?
这么看来, 他就不能控制了
Well, he won't.
马丁内斯负责从赫尔墨斯号操控飞行器
Martinez will pilot the MAV remotely from the Hermes.
我们从来没有尝试过远程操控有人搭载的航天器
We've never had a manned ship controlled remotely before.
但是我对于有这样的机会感到很兴奋啊
But I am excited about the opportunities that I forged.
如果我们搞远程操控, 控制台, 通讯设备也都不需要了
If we go remote, we can lose the control panels, the secondary, tertiary comm systems.
等... 等一下......你要干嘛?
Wait. Wait a second. You want to what?
你想远程操控一个没有备用通讯设施的升空中的航天器?
You want to remotely controlled ascent with no backup comms?
他还没说到最坏的部分呢, 文森特
He's not even got to the bad stuff yet, Vincent.
好吧, 说说最坏的把!
Well, let's get to the bad stuff!
我们需要移除顶部密封层, 窗户, 和面板19.
We need to remove the nose airlock, the windows and Hull Panel 19.
你想把整个飞行器的前面都拆了?
You want to take the front of the ship off?
没错
Sure.
顶部的气密舱有400公斤重呢
The nose airlock alone is 400 kg.
你想用一个连头都没有的飞行器送一个人到太空?
You want to send a man into space without the front of his ship?
不，不是的
Well, no.
我们将用飞船的帆布罩住他
We're going to have him cover it with Hab canvas.
外壳是为了保持舱内的空气
The hull's mostly there to keep the air.
火星的大气很薄，不需要让机舱太流线化
Mars atmosphere is so thin, you don't need a lot of streamlining.
等到飞船的速度快到会受空气阻力影响的时候，
By the time the ship's going fast enough for air resistance to matter,
就应该已经到达没有多少空气的高度了
it'll be high enough that there's practically no air.
你想让他在一块布的包裹下到太空中去
You want to send him into space under a tarp.
没错
Yes.
我能继续了么?
Can I go on?
不行
No.
你他妈的在逗我?
Are you f---ing kidding me?
我觉得他是想说，
You think he means it like,
你在逗我?
Are you kidding me?
- 懂我的意思么? - 哼 - 哼
- You know? - Um- hum.
或者是,"你在逗我?"
Or like, "Are you kidding me?"
有可能是二个
I think it might be the second one.
- 真的么? - 哼
- Really? - Uh- huh.
也有可能是第一个
Could be the first one.
你在逗我?
Are you kidding me?
这么一想，也有可能是第一个
Yeah, it could be the first one.
第538太阳日
SOL 538
基阿帕雷利陨石坑，阿瑞斯4着陆地点
SCHIAPARELLI CRATER Ares 4 LANDING SITE
我知道他们要干嘛
I know what they are doing.
我能猜到他们的每一步计划
I know exactly what they are doing.
他们一直在重复，
'Cause they're keep repeating,
想要作为宇宙旅行的先驱者
Go faster than any man in the history of space travel.
就像是个好的成就一样
Like that's a good thing.
好像就能让我忽视掉他们计划的疯狂程度
Like it would distract me from how insane their plan is.
没错 我确实得飞得比任何人类都快
Yeah. I get to go faster than any man in the history of space travel.
应为你让我在一架敞篷里面发射
Because you're launching me in a convertible.
说实话，更烂，因为我根本没法控制
Actually, it's worse than that, because I won't be able to control that thing.
顺被提一句，物理学家，他们形容速度的时候，
And by the way, physicists, when describing things like acceleration,
不用快不快 所以
do not use the word 'fast'. So...
他们这么做，希望我不产生任何异议
They're doing that, in the hopes that I won't raise any objections.
这么做简直是疯了
It's a lunacy.
你以为，因我喜欢，
You think, because I like the way,
‘宇宙探索史上飞得最快的男人’的说法
'The fastest man in the history of space travel.' sounds.
我还真挺喜欢这称号
I do like the way it sounds.
太尼玛喜欢了
Yeah, I like it a lot.
我不会这么告诉他的
I'm not going to tell them that.
好的吧
Okay.
开始干
Let's do this.
加油
Come on.
[权限拒绝]
贝克和沃格尔去2号气密舱
Beck and Vogel. I want you guys in airlock 2.
在MAV发射之前把外侧的门打开
With the outer door open before the MAV even launches.
收到
Okay.
马丁内斯来操控MAV，约翰森负责总控制
Martinez flies the MAV, Johanssen sysop the ascent.
当我们相遇时，贝克负责去接沃特尼
Once we hit intercept, it's Beck's job to go get Watney.
准备就绪
We're ready.
拦截计划具体是什么样的?
What's the intercept plan?
我们把绳子系成一长条
We finished attaching the tethers into 1 long line
214米长一共
It's 214 meters long.
我将会驾驶这MMU，所以在宇宙中移动不成问题
And I'll have the MMU, so moving around should be easy.
你能应付的对快相对速度是多少?
How fast a relative velocity can you handle?
5米每秒我就能抓住MAV
I can grab the MAV at 5 meters per second.
10米每秒就像网一辆火车上跳
Ten is like jumping onto a moving train.
所以如果比这个速度快，我不一定抓得住
So, any more than that, I might miss.
这样啊，我们有可能有些余地
Well, we may have some leeway.
发射过程共12分钟
The launch takes 12 minutes,
会在拦截前52分钟发射
and it will be 52 minutes before intercept.
一旦马克的引擎关掉，
Once Mark's engines shut off,
我们就能知道拦截地点和相对速度了
we'll know our intercept point and velocity.
沃格尔，你是贝克的替补
Vogel, you're Beck's backup.
如果进行的顺利，你把他们俩一起拽回来
Everything goes well, you pull them on board with the tether.
如果有失误，去救他回来
If anything goes wrong, you go out after him.
没问题
Yep.
好的
Okay.
咱们去把他接回来
Let's go get our boy.
第562太阳日
SOL 561
至不论是谁，好好对这台探险车，他救了我的命 沃特尼
To whom it may concern, take care of this Rover. She saved my life. Watney.
在约翰逊航天中心外有很多紧张焦虑的人们
There's a mood of tension and anxiety here, outside Johnson Space Center.
就像你能看到的一样，很多人来看，
As you can see, many people have gathered here,
这次的拯救行动是否能够成功, 就看我们是否救到了沃特尼
To see whether or not, the mission to retrieve Mark Watney will be a success.
要记得，他们用了某些方式联系到他
Remember, they had some kind of contact with him.
但是我们并不能得到很多信息
but it hasn't been very much.
所以我们必须时刻提醒我们的观众随着时间的继续发展
We have to remind our viewers that we're watching this as it unfolds
我们也会跟观众随时更新动态
and we'll try to keep you up to date as to what exactly is going on.
我们现在听听美航局跟马克·沃特尼的连线
Let's listen in to NASA, making contact with Mark Watney.
大家一起听
Let's listen in.
如果有任何差错，总控制中心能干什么么?
If something goes wrong, What can Mission Control do?
啥都做不了
Not a damn thing.
12分钟之后就要开始了，
It's all happening 12 light minutes away,
就意味着要花他们24分钟得到任何他们想问的问题的答案
which means it takes 24 minutes for them to get the answer to any question they ask.
我们将在12分钟后发射，所以
Our launch is just 12 minutes, so...
他们的靠自己了
They're on their own.
中国航天局 北京总部
CNSA HEADQUARTERS BEIJING
今天，不管是北京人，全世界的人群聚集在电视前，
Today, people have gathered in front of the TVs in Beijing and all over the world,
关注着这个牵动全世界的救援行动
watching attentively at the rescue mission which have caught the attention of the whole world.
这次任务的可行性，是因为中国 NSA的无私
This rescue made possible, is due to China NSA's selfless....
特拉法加广场，伦敦
TRAFALGAR SQUARE LONDON
马克完全一个人孤单的在火星上
Mark has been completely alone on Mars.
根据心理学家的说法
According to psychology expert, they said...
燃油压力正常
Fuel pressure green.
引擎校准完美
Engine alignment perfect.
通没有问题
Communications 5 by 5.
指挥官，我们可以进行与发射检查了
We are ready for preflight checklist, Commander.
总智慧，这里是赫尔墨斯号 我们将按原计划执行
Mission Control, this is Hermes Actual. We will proceed on schedule.
还有2分10秒发射
We are 2 min 10 sec to launch, by the mark.
大概两分钟，沃特尼你怎么样?
About 2 minutes, Watney. How are you doing down there?
棒极了
I'm good.
我等不及上去见你
I'm anxious to get up to you.
感谢你们回来救我
Thanks for coming back for me.
不客气 马上要开始了
Yeah. We're on it.
记得，你会承受很多倍的加速度
Remember, you'll be pulling some serious g's.
晕过去没问题的
So, it's okay to pass out.
马丁内斯将会控制你的飞船
You're in Martinez's hands now.
告诉他，不要让飞船瞎翻来翻去的
Well. Tell that asshole no barrel rolls.
收到，飞行器
Copy that, MAV.
通讯
CAPCOM.
就绪
Go.
远程控制指令
Remote Command.
就绪
Go.
救回
Recovery.
就绪
Go.
副救回
Secondary recovery.
就绪
Go.
飞行员
Pilot.
就绪
Go.
飞行员
Pilot.
就绪
Go.
收到 我们准备出发
Copy. We're a go.
指挥部，我们准备发射了
Mission Control. We are go for launch.
倒计时 10，
T minus 10,
- 9.- 主引擎打火
- 9. - Main engine start.
8.
7.
系泊夹放开
Mooring clamps released.
还5秒，沃特尼 准备好
About 5 seconds, Watney. Hang on.
待会见，指挥官
See you in a few, Commander.
4.
3.
2.
1.
速度，741米每秒
Velocity, 741 meters per second.
高度，1350米
Altitude, 1350 meters.
飞的不够高
It's too low.
我知道，他不让我飞得更高
I know. It's fighting me.
沃特尼，听得到么?
Watney, do you read?
助推器分离完毕
Booster separation complete.
速度，850. 高度，1843.
Velocity, 850. Altitude, 1843.
他离目标的高度差太远了
He's way below target altitude.
差多少?
How- How far below?
正在查
Checking.
沃特尼，收到么?
Watney, do you read?
他估计晕过去了
He's probably passed out
他承受了12个G的加速度 让他缓一缓
He pulled 12 g's on the ascent. Give him a few minutes.
收到
Copy that.
3秒主助推器熄火，
Main shutdown in 3,
2,
1.
熄火
Shutdown.
回到自动导航
Back to automatic guidance.
已确认熄火
Shutdown confirmed.
燃料储备用尽
Fuel reserve depleted.
沃特尼,
Watney
收到么?
do you read?
看来可能有一些通讯上的问题
There seems to be some sort of problem with the transmission.
我有时间延迟
I have interval pings.
拦截速度将会是11米每秒
Intercept velocity will be 11 meters per second.
我能接下来
I can make that work.
距离差将会是
Distance at intercept will be...
我们将会相距68公里
We'll be 68 km apart.
68 千米
68 km?
他刚刚说68公里?
Did she just say 68 km?
别瞎闹，解决眼前的问题
Come on, guys, keep it together. Work the problem.
约翰森，拦截时间?
Johanssen, time to intercept?
还有39分钟12秒
39 minutes 12 seconds.
马丁内斯，不如把我们的助推器指向他的方向?
Martinez, what if we point our thrusters in the same direction?
就看你想保留多少燃料了
Well, it depends on how much fuel you want to save
回地球的时候还要调整高度
for the altitude adjustments for the trip home.
你需要多少?
How much do you need?
我应该能用20%剩下的燃料办到
I can get by with about 20% of what we have left.
如果我们用75.5%剩下的燃料调整高度，
If we use 75.5% of remaining altitude adjustment fuel,
就能让距离差为0.
That'll bring the intercept range to zero.
干吧
Do this.
等一下 虽说距离为零了，
Hang on. It brings the range to zero,
但是拦截相对速度将会变成42米每秒
but the intercept velocity will be 42 meters per second.
太他妈快了
And it's way too fast.
现在就需要在39分钟里思考出来怎么慢下来
Then, we have 39 minutes to figure out how to slow down.
马丁内斯，点火
Martinez, burn the jets.
收到
Copy that.
飞行器呼叫 赫尔墨斯号
Mav to Hermes.
沃特尼?
确认
Affirmative.
你状况如何?
What's your status?
我胸口好疼
My chest hurts.
可能肋骨断了
I have broken my ribs.
你怎么样?
How are you?
我们正在考虑怎么救你 过程中出了个小问题
We're working on getting to you. There was a complication during the launch.
收到
Copy that.
这样啊，什么样的小问题?
Well, how bad is it?
我们搞定了拦截距离的问题，但是相对速度还是不行
Well, we corrected the intercept range, but we got a problem with intercept velocity.
速度差多少?
How big a problem?
42米每秒
42 meters per second.
这，
Well,
妈的
shit.
指挥官，我有个点子
Commander, I have an idea.
说吧，mark
Go ahead, Mark.
如果我能找到一个尖锐物
Well, If I can find something sharp in here
我可以在我的宇航服上戳一个洞
and poke a hole in the glove of my EVA suit.
然后就能用溢出的气体的当作助推
I could use the escaping air as a thruster
然后飞过去找你
and fly towards you.
应该不会太难操控，我打算在我的胳膊上戳个洞
It would be easy to control, because it would be on my arm.
我怎么不觉得你能控制得了呢
I can't see you having any control if you did that.
你只能目测拦截地点，然后你还控制不了助推方向
You'd be eyeballing the intercept using a thrust vector you can barely controls
没错没错，说的都对
Yes. Yes. Those are all very good points.
但是，想想看：
But, consider this:
我就能像钢铁侠一样飞了
I'd get to fly around like Iron Man.
指挥官
Commander,
就这样吧，用钢铁侠计划
let's go Iron Man.
这可是意料之外
This is unexpected, LOS.
通讯丢失 待命
Communication lost. Standby.
这可能不是一个坏主意
Maybe it's not the worst idea.
不，这就是一个坏主意，不能再坏了
No, it is the worst idea. It's the worst idea ever.
不是他说的那个
Not what he said.
用大气作为助推
Using atmosphere as thrust.
要是把阀门给炸了会怎么样?
What happens if we blow the VAL?
什么鬼? 你想打开气密舱?
What? You want to open the vehicular airlock?
这样会给我们一个很不错的减速
It'd give us a good kick.
但是会把飞船的密闭舱给炸掉
Yeah, but it will also blow the nose off the ship.
然后所有的空气就都跑了，然后我们不想死
And all the air will leave, and we need air to not die.
我们可以密封好栈桥和反应室
We'll seal the bridge and the reactor room.
其他所有地方都变真空
Everywhere else will go vacuo.
沃格尔
Vogel.
说吧指挥官
Go ahead, Commander.
我想你回来做一个…炸弹
I need you to come inside and make a... bomb.
你说什么指挥官?
Uh. Again, Commander?
你是个化学家
You're a chemist.
你能用飞船上的东西做个炸弹么?
Can you make a bomb with what you have on board?
应该行
Probably.
但是我觉得应该提醒一下你
But I feel obliged to mention that setting off an explosive device
在宇航飞船上引爆东西是个坏点子
in a spacecraft is a terrible terrible idea.
等等 你们不等我回去就要搞炸弹?
Hang on. You guys making a bomb without me?
懂了，但是你能造个炸弹么?
Copy that. Can you do it?
可以
Yeah.
休斯顿，我们要故意冲破阀门
Houston. Be advised we're going to deliberately breach the VAL
然后提供哦拿一个反向的助推 - 你说什么?
- to produce some reverse thrust. - What?
贝克，别脱你的宇航服，跟约翰森在1号气密舱见面
Beck, leave your suit on, meet Johanssen in airlock 1.
我们将把外面的门打开
We'll open the outer door.
我需要你把炸弹放在内侧的门上
I need you to place the charge on the inner door.
然后从外壳爬回2号气密舱
Climb back to airlock 2 along the hull.
好的，我这就过去
Copy. I'm on my way.
我到了，指挥官
I'm in, Commander.
收到
Copy that.
沃格尔，你在哪?
Vogel, where are you?
- 我在厨房 - 好的吧
- I'm in the kitchen. - Okay.
指挥官
Commander,
不能让你们尽力这么多，
I can't let you go through with this.
我准备戳洞了
I am prepared to cut the suit.
别
Absolutely not.
是这样的, 你看, 我这个人嘛, 很自私
Well, see. The thing is, I'm selfish.
我想回到家之后所有人的纪念都只是关于我的
I want all the memorials back home to be about me.
仅仅纪念我
Just me.
我就不应该来救他
I should have left this guy on Mars.
嘿！
Hey.
- 这是糖? - 没错
- Sugar? - Yeah.
你能帮我拿一下么?
Can you hold this?
液氧
Liquid oxygen.
再加一些去渍的, 这里面含有氨
Add some stain remover that contains ammonia.
现在这个玩意
This thing here,
比炸药棒可强5倍呢
is 5 times stronger than a stick of dynamite.
我们怎么引爆他?
How do we activate it?
你可以把这个连接到其中一个开关上
You can connect this to one of your lighting panels.
小心点
Careful.
打开1号气密舱
Open airlock 1.
我正在前往贝克的途中
I'm on the way to Beck.
伙计们，我只希望这是一个好主意
I just hope this is a good idea, guys.
- 这就是 - 打开1号气密舱
- It is. - Open A1.
嗨
Hi.
拿好了吗
You have it?
你要确保在这个东西爆炸之前离开这里
Make sure you're not in here when this thing goes off.
嘿
Hey.
在太空外面
Be Careful out there.
注意安全
In space.
不要告诉别人
Don't tell anyone I did that.
炸弹已安放
Bomb set.
正在离开1号气密舱
Leaving airlock 1.
伙计们, 我正在计算让阀门爆炸的最佳时间
Guys, I'm running the numbers, even with optimum VAL blow,
我们正在偏离我们的角度
We're going to be off on our angle.
约翰森, 拦截距离是多少
What's the intercept distance? Johanssen?
大约260米
260 meters to approximate.
这太远了
It's too far.
指挥官
Commander?
马丁内斯, 离门近点
Martinez, close the door.
打开D3
Open D3.
让它一直开着
Leave it open.
打开B2
Open B2.
约翰森
Johanssen,
距离阀门还有多久爆炸
Time to VAL blow after initiate?
15秒
15 seconds.
我们知道如何拉近距离
We sure know how to cut it close.
指挥官
Commander.
距离太远了, 我要出去了
The distance is too far, I'm going out.
- 我可以做到的 - 这可不是比赛
- I can do this. - It's not a debate.
我是不会拿我的船员的生命冒险的
I'm not risking another crew member.
贝克回来了
Beck's returned.
约翰森, 还有多久引爆炸弹
Johanssen, initiate the bomb.
10秒
10 seconds.
系上安全带
Strap in.
5秒
5.
4秒
4.
3秒
3.
- 减速 - 2秒
- Deceleration! - 2,
1秒
1.
激活控制板41
Activating the panel 41.
封锁舱安全
Bridge seal holding.
- 有什么损伤 - 先不用担心这个
- What's the damage? - Worry about that later.
相对加速度是多少
What's the relative velocity?
12米每秒
12 meters per second.
收到
Copy.
把我绑起来
Hook me up.
好了
Done.
我看到了飞行器
I've visual of the MAV.
拦截距离是多少
What's the intercept range?
正在查
I'm checking.
312米
312 meters.
你刚才是说312米吗
Did you say 312?
好的, 我到了向你们招手
Okay. I'll wave at you guys as I go by.
哦
Oh.
我够不着你, 马克 你离我太远了
I can't get to you, Mark. You're too far.
- 我抓不住你 - 我知道
- I'm not going to make it - I know.
贝克, 把我解绑 我要跟着他
Beck, unhook me. I'm going after him.
指挥官, 我能搞定
Commander, I got this.
马克, 请汇报
Mark, report.
马上就来, 指挥官
On my way, Commander.
该死
Damn it.
约翰森, 我对马克的相对速度是多少
Johanssen, what's my relative velocity to Mark?
5.2 米每秒
5.2 meters per second.
收到 正在调整
Copy. Adjusting course.
3.1 米每秒
3.1 meters per second.
距离目标还有24米
Distance to target 24 meters.
还有11米
11 meters to target.
6米
6 meters.
坚持住, 马克
Hold on, Mark.
来
Come on.
我抓住他了!
I got him!
我抓住他了
I got him.
做得好, 钢铁侠
Way to go, Iron Man.
贝克, 拉我们进去
Beck, pull us in.
很高兴见到你
It's good to see you.
你……
You...
的音乐品味……
have... terrible taste
太烂了
in music.
休斯顿, 这里是赫尔墨斯行动
Houston, this is Hermes Actual.
我们接上他了
We got him.
耶!
YEAH!
沃特尼安全了
Watney is secure.
好! 好! 好!
YES! YES! YES!
和外太空的马克·沃特尼联系上了
Contact in outer space, with Mark Watney.
历时良久, 他们终于完成了许多人所认为的不可能
After a very long time, they have done what many people thought was impossible.
特别庆祝：马克·沃特尼成功获救
Special Gratulation: Mark Watney has been successfully rescued.
马克·沃特尼获救了, 这是一次不可思议的任务
Mark Watney has been rescued. This has been an incredible mission.
抓住他
Get a hold of him.
嘿嘿, 帅哥
Hey- Hey, handsome.
贝克, 把舱门关上
Beck, close the hatch.
嘿, 各位!
Hey, guys!
休斯顿, 6名成员安全上船
Houston, 6 crews safely aboard.
这是个伟大的时刻, 对于国家, 对于世界
This is a huge moment for this nation, for the world
当然, 对于国际太空旅行来说亦然
and, in deed, for international space travel.
- 嘿 - 嘿
- Hey. - Hey.
天哪!
Oh god!
你耽误了不少工夫啊, 哥们儿
There's a little sloth going on over there, man.
我知道, 都一年半没洗澡了
I know. I haven't had a shower for a year and a half.
别逗我笑, 我断了根肋骨
Don't make me laugh. I have a broken rib.
你好啊
Hey, there.
日安, 长官
Good day, sir.
- 真是荣幸, 长官 - 长官好
- It's an honor, sir. - Sir.
- 长官好 - 长官好
- Sir. - Sir.
早安, 长官
Good morning, sir.
欢迎来到宇航员预备计划
Welcome to the Astronaut Candidate Program.
现在请注意听, 因为可能会救你一命
Now pay attention, because this could save your life.
相信我, 我很懂自己在说什么
Trust me. I know what I'm talking about.
好, 让我先把几件事说清楚, 就现在
Alright. Let me get a few things out of the way, right off the bat.
是的, 我确实在一个荒芜的星球上活下来了, 靠着用自己的屎种地
Yes, I did in fact survive on a deserted planet by farming in my own shit.
是的, 其实比听起来更糟糕, 所以, 咱们还是别再提这茬了
Yes, it's actually worse than it sound. So, let's not talk about that ever again.
另一个我常被问及的是
The other question I get most frequently is.
当我在那里, 孑然一身
When I was up there stranded by myself,
我想过会死去吗？
Did I think I was going to die?
是的, 当然
Yes, absolutely.
而且这是你在加入的时候就要知道的, 因为这会发生在你身上
And that's what you need to know going in, because it's going to happen to you.
这是太空, 它不会顺着你
This is space. It does not cooperate.
有时候, 就会屋漏偏逢连夜雨
At some point, everything's going to go south on you.
屋漏偏逢连夜雨, 你会说：“就这样了”
Everything's going to go south and you're going to say "This is it."
我就这么完了
That is how I end.
这时你要么接受
Now you can either accept that,
要么去工作
or you can get to work.
就是这么回事
That's all it is.
你只要开始
You just begin.
你算算数, 解决掉一个问题
You do the math. You solve one problem
然后你解决下一个
and you solve the next one,
然后又一个
and then the next.
如果你解决足够多的问题, 你就能回家了
And If you solve enough problems, you get to come home.
好, 有问题吗？
Alright. Questions?
一旦指挥中心完成了飞行前检查
Once Mission Control complete their preflight checks,
我们就开始发射程序
we'll begin launch procedures.
阿瑞斯5号将与赫尔墨斯号对接
The Ares 5 team will rendezvous with the Hermes
约于发射后48分钟
approximately 48 minutes after launch.
从那时起, 他们将进行为期414天的太空旅行
From there, they'll have 414 days of space travel ahead of them.
阿瑞斯5号较之前任务, 目标有所改变吗？
Have the goals changed from the previous mission to the Ares 5 program?
以及你们本次希望有何成就？
And what do you hope to achieve this time around?
嗯, 不, 阿瑞斯计划的目标从未改变
Well, no. The goals has always been the same for the Ares Program.
这次, 当然, 我们希望一次就能把所有宇航员带回来
This time, of course we hope to bring all the astronauts back at the same time.
- 指挥, 引导人员检查完毕 - 收到, 引导人员
- Flight, Guidance check complete. - Copy, Guidance.
我是指挥, 我们按时发射
This is Flight. We are go for launch on schedule.
最后一次航空服务检查完毕
Final Aerial Service Check are complete.
万事俱备, 只欠发射
As everything remains a go. Fvor the launch of the Ares 5.
20秒
20 seconds.
继续倒数
Proceeding with the count.
倒计时10
T minus 10.
9.
主引擎点火
Main engine start.
7, 6, 5, 4
7, 6, 5, 4,
3, 2, 1
3, 2, 1.
升空
And liftoff.
此时, 阿瑞斯5号的成员开启了美国太空探索新的一页
As the crew of the Ares 5 begin the next chapter of America's space exploration.
压力正常
Pressure look good.
呜!
Woo!
哇, 漂亮
Wow, good shot.
终于, 在解救宇航员马克·沃特尼5年后
There it is. 5 years after the rescue of astronaut Mark Watney,
阿瑞斯5号奔向了火星
the Ares 5 is on it's way to Mars.